<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Instructions to a nobleman's daughter concerning religion at first designed for one, now directed to all of that rank, and useful to young persons of quality, and others of that sex : with sacramental and other suitable devotions / by John Provoste.</title>
            <author>Provoste, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 131 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 67 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56118</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3877</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R35367</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15265156</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15265156</idno>
            <idno type="VID">103318</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56118)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 103318)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1192:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Instructions to a nobleman's daughter concerning religion at first designed for one, now directed to all of that rank, and useful to young persons of quality, and others of that sex : with sacramental and other suitable devotions / by John Provoste.</title>
                  <author>Provoste, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 120 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W.R. for D. Brown ... and L. Stokey ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: prelim. p. [2]</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Girls --  Prayer-books and devotions.</term>
               <term>Women --  Prayer-books and devotions.</term>
               <term>Devotional literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:103318:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:103318:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Inſtructions TO A <hi>Nobleman's Daughter</hi> CONCERNING RELIGION.</p>
            <p>At firſt deſigned for One, now di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to all of that Rank, and uſeful young Perſons of Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and others of that Sex.</p>
            <p>WITH <hi>Sacramental, and other ſuitable DEVOTIONS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>John Provoſte.</hi> M. A.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>W. R.</hi> for <hi>D. Brown</hi> at the <hi>Black Swan</hi> and <hi>Bible</hi> without <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple-bar,</hi> and <hi>L. Stokey</hi> at the <hi>Golden-key</hi> over againſt the <hi>Muſe-gate</hi> at <hi>Charing-croſs.</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:103318:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge. 5. line 19. read deſpiſed, p. 8. l. 14. r. Subjects. l. 22. r. Catechiſm. p. 10. l. 14. r. capable. l. 25. r. reading. p. 12. l. 12. after Bleſſings 2 Comma. l. 13. r. Baptized. l. 19. after underſtood put a Period. l. 21. r. may. l. 25. r. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance. l. 26. r. not. p. 16. l. 10. r. Epicurus. p. 17. l. 6. r. no. l. 12. r. Joy. p. 18. l. 6. r. bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable. l. 20. after Pray put a Semicolon. l. 21. after Heaven put a Comma. p. 20. l. 2. r. under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. l. 13. r. faſhioned. p. 22. l. 13. r. Eyes ſee. p. 28. l. 6. r. me. p. 33. l. 14. r. ineffectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al. p. 34. l. 18. r. to. l. 20. r. Wiſe. p. 38. l. 12. r. then. l. 19. r. earlieſt. p. 39. l. 12. r. them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. p. 49. l. 2. r. Images. p. 69. l. 23. r. 2 Sacrament. p. 70. l. 16. r. John. p. 18. l. 4. r. Prov. 31.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:103318:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Honourable THE LADY —</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Hope your Ladyſhip has all the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction which the Country can give to any one, or your own Expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion promiſed to your ſelf, and whereas Expectation is often raiſed above En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment, I hope Enjoyment now riſes high, and ſurmounts all your gay No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I know, and methinks at this very Inſtant I have a ſenſe and a ſhare of that Joy which your Ladyſhip is affected with upon your Retreat from the Town: Let that Joy encreaſe, and in the Country, and in every Place, and in every thing let it ſtill be grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:103318:3"/>and ſo much rather, becauſe it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> greater than you deſerve, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſame Virtue and Prudence, which make you deſerve it, will be ſure to make your J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, and all Things very Innocent. I have ſometimes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed your Ladyſhips Condeſcenſion; and with that eaſie Mildneſs, which you ſhew <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n all Occaſions, and with which you have already learned to bear all Evils, you have ſeemed to bear the Trouble of Reading my Inſtructions: But you never had ſo much Advantage from my Writing, as now, to ſatisfie for the Trouble, nor I ſo good Occaſion to give it. I doubt not but you will have the ſame Thought of the Occaſion, I have my ſelf; and ſo I may hope for an Effect equal to it. I have often beheld your growing Piety with a ſecret and riſing Satisfaction, and I cannot but endeavour to continue and improve my own Satisfaction, by Exhorting, Adviſing, Intreating your Ladyſhip to continue and improve your Piety. Seeing I have ſo great a pleaſure in
<pb facs="tcp:103318:3"/>the View, I am become a Party, and my own Intereſt, that I may have it ſtill, engages me to do all I can for the enlargement of a thing which gives it: A thing which is ſo good in it ſelf, and ſo advantageous to you, and which you ſeem to Repay and Reward for all its Advantage by the graceful Light and Beauty you reflect upon it; when like a well-ſet Diamond, it appears in you and borrows from you. I have with ſo much Pleaſure obſerved that Piety, which was your own original Growth; and then with how much more ſhall I obſerve, and with how Innocent a Pride, any part of your piety hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which has been planted in your Mind by my Endeavour, and which being placed in ſo Rich, and Noble Ground, muſt there be to a Wonder fruitful by your own. I ſhall ſee it with a Joy refined and high, with a greater than that of the King in Hiſtory, when he ſaw the fair and goodly Tree, his own Hand had ſet, and then his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in Surveying the Growth of the
<pb facs="tcp:103318:4"/>Tree ſcarce was equal to this of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring that he had ſet it. I ſhould think my ſelf to do Service to the World, in doing this to your Ladyſhip, who may be ſo uſeful to the World; and to Religion, by the Influence of your Example; by the Authority of your Intereſt, and by the Prudence of your Zeal to make uſe of both, as of every thing, to the beſt and moſt worthy Purpoſes. So ſhall I have, in this my Writing, that glorious Hope of doing the greateſt Good by the ſhorteſt way, to many in one; as when the chief City is taken, all the Neighbouring Country very often comes in by an eaſie Surren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, or is Conquered with it: And ſurely the thing will as much become your Quality as it will be promoted by your Zeal, that there ſhould be a nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous Train to attend you in your Courſe of Virtue, and in your Journey towards Heaven. All the Religious Things, when carried on by you to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, will at the ſame time be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, and become more inviting by
<pb facs="tcp:103318:4"/>their paſſing through your Hands, as Liquors take a fragrant, and more grateful taſt from the Veſſel through which they paſs. When there have been already ſuch ſhining Effects of your Virtue, and when the Cauſe is ſo fruitful and ſure, ſo generous and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ready to produce them, I may oblige my ſelf and the World by all my pleaſing and moſt agreeable Preſages, and yet my Gift of Foretelling may not be, like thoſe Effects, extraordinary; as they who pretend to the Faculty of declaring things to come, do little more than argue from the ſame Cauſes to the ſame Effects. The Country gives you lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and you want nothing for the rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing a Good-will, to read ſuch things as this before you; and the Country gives not only leiſure, but a new Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument for Religion, becauſe there <hi>the inviſible things of God are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood by the things which are made,</hi> By every Flower you gather, and every Fruit you eat, by the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Herb you tread on, and the leaſt
<pb facs="tcp:103318:5"/>thing you ſee in the Garden, or in the Field. The Country has already no little part in your Favour, it has ſo large a Place in your Affections, that it could lend ſome even to things leſs Grateful; the moſt diſagreeable things would ceaſe to be ſo, when this ſhould recommend them to you: But ſurely the Country will have new Endear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and more lively Charms, when you ſhall begin to apprehend it, as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving all the convenience, not only to breath, but to think more freely too, and as having at the Leiſure, and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and Enlargment, not only for many other Purpoſes, but for one thing which you love more than the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and then all things, for Religion. Thus I have frankly declared the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of theſe Papers, and your Lady<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip will generouſly pardon the length of them, and all their Faults; whereof I think my ſelf to be guilty with Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority; becauſe the Deſign is ſuch as gives the higheſt Authority to this, and to any other Action, and to all the
<pb facs="tcp:103318:5"/>harmleſs Errors of it. When I have freely confeſt the Purpoſe of my Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, (and this no worſe than what you hear) your Ladyſhip will give me leave to ſpeak freely upon it, with all that plainneſs which good Deſigns always covet, and well-meant Inſtructions chuſe, and the true Ends of both re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire. Then may I be allowed to ſpeak without the Ceremony of Addreſs to your Sex, and your Quality; that I may thus teach you to forget your Greatneſs, which you ſeem already to know ſo little of, and to be your ſelf almoſt a ſtranger to: The nice Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of it is to be laid aſide for the Time by me in Writing, and by you in Reading. This Boon I ask at the opening of my Diſcourſe, as the Great Council asks (at the firſt opening of it,) Freedom of Acceſs and of Speech in Debates upon Things of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Good. As to the Grandeur of Birth, you have ſo much of the Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity which Virtue gives, that the other is almoſt ſunk in this, and the greater
<pb facs="tcp:103318:6"/>Light ſcarce allows the leſs to be ſeen. As to the gaudy Honours of the ſolemn Regard which ſuch a Birth does al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways claim, your Ladyſhip is to leave this part to others; as that is not, like Virtue, <hi>your own,</hi> ſo the eſteem which it ſhould have is not to be from your ſelf; and yet to that an Eſteem is due: Indeed <hi>Moſes</hi> would never have <hi>refuſed to be called the Son of</hi> Pharaoh<hi>'s Daughter,</hi> and the Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of a King, if he had been the thing which he was called, he would not have Renounced the innocent Glories of ſuch a Relation, as he did not deſpiſe the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorious <hi>Reproach of Chriſt,</hi> if the Pretence would not have been falſe Heraldry, and the Advantage only the <hi>enjoying the Pleaſures of Sin for a Seaſon.</hi> But ſo great, Madam, is your ſhare, and ſo rich you are, in high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Things, that you may reſerve e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for your ſelf, if you reſign your Claim of Birth to them who have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing beſides it, to them who are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to be ſtill what they were born,
<pb facs="tcp:103318:6"/>and, as if they were only over-grown infants of one Days Age, have made no Progreſs ſince the firſt Minutes of Life. I now beg leave to tell stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, that they are not to take the length of your Underſtanding from that of your Age, and to tell your ſelf, that I have ſo great an Opinion of your Underſtanding, and ſo little of my own, as to think I could not eaſily Write any thing upon ſuch a Subject above your reach: So great is my O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion too of your Piety, as to think I could not eaſily preſcribe any thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove your Practice. I am ſure, nothing which can have any part in your Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous well-being, though never ſo high, can be above my Wiſhes, and it is no more beyond my Attempts to enforce it, than beyond yours to do it. I am ſure again, if you are to have every thing I wiſh, you cannot have too much of that Wiſdom, <hi>which (according to the Wiſe, though Apocryphal Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters) reaches from one end to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:103318:7"/>mightily, and ſweetly orders all things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My willing Conſent is always ready for all your Inclinations, and my joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with you as ready for all your Service. But I would, of all things, carry on the pleaſing Harmony of your good Actions in Conſort with you; in nothing ſo much you deſire, in nothing ſo much you ſhall have the Concurrence and united Force of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Madam,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Ladyſhips moſt Humble Servant. J. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:103318:7"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have ask'd your leave to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect Inſtructions to you, and now I preſently take it, as rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to make uſe of it as you are, I am ſure, to grant it, who, as you are too generous to deny any thing which ſhould advance the Good of others, ſo are too wiſe to refuſe that which would promote your own.</p>
            <p>The Firſt Advice which I ſhall offer to you, ſhall be in the firſt thing which Religion taught you.</p>
            <p>Let the Catechiſm never be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten: Though it is learn'd in Childhood, it is to be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred ſtill in all the other parts of our Age; therefore indeed learn'd in Childhood, that it may not be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, and that it may be uſeful
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:103318:8"/>ever afterwards: As when the Pilot has Sailed very far, and very often, yet he is not to throw away his Compaſs, nor to Sail without it. Religion begins thus in Childhood; if in that Age it begins, much more in our Age of Underſtanding it is to be continued, and to be improved, as other things are not leſs, but they become greater and ſtronger too by Time. Religion is much more to be continued in all the Scenes of Life beyond our Childhood, becauſe we afterwards come to the Age of Practice, which is its chief deſign, and becauſe our Underſtanding is more accompliſh'd afterwards, and ſo we are then more capable of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancements in that which is the moſt noble Exerciſe of our Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, in Religion. Indeed the firſt uſe of our Reaſon, the firſt open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it is to be in that, becauſe it will be more prepared for a Progreſs in Knowledge, and the Child, the yet imperfect Creature, for Attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:103318:8"/>in Perfection, by making the firſt ſteps in the Underſtanding of Him who is the Fountain of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and of all Perfection. A par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular right He has to the firſt Fruits of our Reaſon, becauſe it is more particularly derived from God, and it is more the Image of Him from whom it comes, and becauſe the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of him from whom it derives its own, is a Principle our Reaſon is acquainted with as ſoon as any, and therefore it ſhould be as ſoon ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the Worſhip and the Knowledge of Him. If our Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, amongſt its many Paſtimes, is to have Religion for its Buſineſs; if that Light and thoughtleſs Age is in this alone to become ſerious and wiſely Active, this much more ſhould be our Exerciſe, when our Age has all the ſteady Thought and Reflection, and when all our Thought is directed to Buſineſs, and Things of high and ſerious Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and when the more we think,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:103318:9"/>we are carried ſtill farther into Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. If our Reaſon at the firſt glimmering and dawning of it is to begin its day, as we ſhould every one of our Life, with Religion, much more is this to have enlarg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with our Reaſon, and to be <hi>the greater Light to rule the Day;</hi> the Worſhip of the Father of Lights, is ſurely to be much more then our Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe, when we are in ſo much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter condition to perform it.</p>
            <p>I ſpeak thus of Religious Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that, when gained in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, it is not to be loſt in the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing part of our Age, becauſe too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny think it may then well be loſt, and it was intended only for our Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and <hi>when we were children, we were in Bondage under Rudiments, we ſpoke as Children, underſtood as Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, thought as Children,</hi> but we are <hi>to put away afterwards childiſh things.</hi> How great, alaſs, the Miſunderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and how fatal the effect, if there be no recovery from it! How
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:103318:9"/>much do they, who thus miſunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, ſeem Induſtrious to prove themſelves Children ſtill? How much happier would they be, if they were ſo indeed? They would then have ſomething like Excuſe; now they have not.</p>
            <p>All that we did, and learn'd in the more ſerious Undertakings of our Childhood was only deſigned for Diſcipline and Method to diſpoſe us for the doing and learning more here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, as he can never be Rich, who keeps not that which he has gain'd, and he can never be Skilful in any Art or Science, who forgets the firſt Notions of it he once was taught. A Father of the Church ſaid upon a like Occaſion, <hi>nothing is to be diſpiſed by thoſe who are to be inſtructed, and led into the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of things; for if they look upon the firſt Elements as little things, how ſhall they attain the perfect and great things in knowledge?</hi> Theſe early things which the Church has taught us, are not Scaffold work, to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:103318:10"/>down again, but Foundation, and he that would take away the Foundation, when the Houſe is near the being, finiſh'd, would only un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermine it, and never finiſh it. Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever diſcards the knowledge of the Catechiſm, when he is no more a Child, he either at the ſame time re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounces all knowledge of Religion, (but ſurely, if that knowledge were neceſſary in Childhood, it is much more neceſſary afterwards) or he at the ſame time deſigns a much high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Knowledge in Religion; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is ſtill going forward, he leaves the firſt behind him, not as too heavy, but as too light, or little to carry with him. Indeed he muſt not here <hi>forget thoſe things which are be hind,</hi> if he will <hi>reach forth to thoſe things which Are before,</hi> if he will <hi>preſs towards the Mark of the Prize of the high Calling.</hi> The more he values thoſe other things he would underſtand, the more he is to value theſe firſt things, without
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:103318:10"/>which he cannot underſtand the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the more Knowledge he has attained, the more humble he is, or ſhould be, and ſo not apt to deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſe the meaneſt Truth as well as Perſon; be owes the greater regard to theſe original Truths, to which he owes all his higheſt Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Indeed they are not the meaneſt Truths, they are the firſt in Order and Dignity, as well as in Time and Place, becauſe they are the Doctrines of things neceſſary to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and no Good ſo great as Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, no Truth ſo great, as that which teaches things neceſſary to it. The other Doctrines are the Iſſues of theſe by a natural Conſequence, and ſo they cannot be nobler than theſe, till the Off-ſpring ſhall claim more Honour than Parents, from whom they derive all they have. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts of Religion are but ſo many ſeveral Streams that flow from theſe, which therefore ſhould have all the Reverence from us, as Fountains had
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:103318:11"/>ſo much from the <hi>Heathens,</hi> were Sacred, and were Adored.</p>
            <p>The Doctrines of the Catechiſm are very far from being thoſe of the loweſt Rank, they have ſo much the Character of the Scripture from whence we received them (as Fruits have the Nature of the Soil wherein they grow) that however there are things in the Catechiſm for the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, there are alſo many for the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and moſt manly Underſtanding: The things are ſo high, that they are ſubjects more of Belief, then of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry, and yet when they have My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery enough to puzzle the Enquirer, they have at the ſame time Evidence enough to baffle the Unbeliever; Evidence, like that of Witneſſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a Malefactor, to Condemn him. The Doctrines ſtill are great, however the ſtyle of the Catechiſm, like that of the Scripture, be very plain, as the greateſt Perſon may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in the plaineſt Dreſs: There is ſo much more of the nicer Art, to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:103318:11"/>reduce ſublime and awful things to eaſie and familiar Words, and there is more Authority in ſuch a Language, as there is often a more prevailing Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in a condeſcending and lowly Behaviour. That No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Perſon had a very juſt Opinion<note n="†" place="margin">The Lady <hi>Catherine</hi> Manners, afterwards Marchioneſs of
<hi>Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingham.</hi>
               </note> of our Catechiſm, who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged it to be a plain Summa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of ſaving Truth, and being of a Roman-Catholick Family, and Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, ſhe ſeemed in this Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment to give a generous Pledg, that there ſhould be Succeſs to their Endeavours, who were Zealous to teach her new and better Principles. The Religious Beginnings of Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood are in things neceſſary to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that our happy End, the End of our Faith may be in Salvation it ſelf, our Chriſtian Beginning is in things more neceſſary, as in the firſt part of a Feaſt we find the Meats which have more ſubſtance, and nouriſh more. Our firſt entrance
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:103318:12"/>is in the needful things of Belief and Knowledge, both becauſe this Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief and Knowledge are the Root to all the goodly Branches of Religion, and there muſt be firſt a Root, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there can be an enlargement of the Tree into ſpreading Branches, and uſeful Fruit, and becauſe the former Time of our Age is not ſo ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of, nor has ſuch Occaſion and Exerciſe for the ſeveral good Works, which are the other chief parts of Chriſtian Duty; but it is already capable of Knowledge, which ſhould prepare us for them.</p>
            <p>That being planted in the Houſe of the Lord, you may flouriſh in the Courts of the Houſe of our God, in His Church, and you my bring forth more Fruit in your Age, that you may grow in Grace, and in the Knowledge of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, your reading over the Catechiſm once every Month of your Life, and your reading it with all the Wiſdom, and careful Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:103318:12"/>of your more perfect Age, would be a moſt uſeful Office; when you may be above the giving an account of it to others, you can never, in a Life of all thoſe Years I wiſh you, out-live the Neceſſity of giving it to your ſelf, and to God. There is a Precept to all, even to the oldeſt Chriſtians, for the being ready al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways to give account to others, to give an Anſwer to every Man that asks a Reaſon of the Hope which is in them. So needful is the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of this firſt Knowledge, that you cannot know any thing elſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, without having ſtill an Eye to this, and then ſteering by it; you are to take it with you wherever you go, in whatever you do: It is the Standard, by which all your Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is to be tryed, and it is the Rule, to which all your Practice hereafter is to be reconciled.</p>
            <p>As the Catechiſm is always to be well remembred, ſo is it to be well conſidered by you. No part of it
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:103318:13"/>you are to conſider more, than your Vow in Baptiſm, and the Explaining of the Commandments in the Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm; the Performance of which Commandments (ſo explained) is one great part of the Performance of that Vow, and the great, the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Exerciſe of your wiſeſt Age, and of the beſt Endeavours in all the Time which is to come, and I hope with a long Train after it of Days and Bleſſings upon your doing that which you were not only Baptized, but you were born to the Performance of.</p>
            <p>I know you already underſtand very much in Religion, and often have I obſerved, and always rejoyced in obſerving how much you un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood. But now, That the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Age of your Life, as the firſt was of the World, may be a Golden one, That your Knowledge may riſe to Practice in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, and your Practice may advance to Perfection; that you may not be diſcouraged in the Practice (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:103318:13"/>in the beginning of it.) I beg leave to adviſe you, who under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand already ſo much of Religion, not to miſunderſtand the Deſign thereof, as if Melancholy were a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Effect of Religion, or were a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Duty of it, as if it denied us a moderate Liberty in worldly Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and required that we ſhould deny our ſelves this Liberty. Were ſuch a Notion of Religion a true one, and embraced as true, it might have a diſmal Conſequence, that nothing of Religion, beſides this Notion, might be embraced by Perſons of your Age, and Sex, and Quality. Your Age, as well as Sex, may be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to love things leſs difficult or ſevere, and not to abhor Diverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Mirth; your Quality gives a Right, almoſt a Birth-right to that, to which your other Circumſtances may give ſome Inclination, to Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and harmleſs Enjoyment. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy is very far from being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, it is forbidden by Religion;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:103318:14"/>Exceſs of that, as much forbidden, as the Exceſs of Mirth. Religion for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids not Enjoyment, but abuſe, which is no part of the Enjoyment, which indeed does leſſen it, that, and not Religion hinders all. So far Religion is from hindering, that in its Deſign it promotes, and in its Practice, in the preſent Act it gives a chearful Mind, and this is one great, this is one preſent Reward to the Practice of it: Surely none has ſo much cauſe as the Pious Man for a chearful Mind, and O let him ever have it, let there be no Pretence or Bar againſt his having that which is thus his right, and which God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf deſires he ſhould have. As there was a famous Maſter who would have Pictures of Joy to be placed round his School, that his Scholars might have Images of Delight in their Minds, and Knowledge might become a more inviting Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure to thoſe who came thither to make Addreſſes to it. Religion is a
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:103318:14"/>thing of great delight in its Nature, and it is never otherwiſe, but when it is made otherwiſe by us, as the moſt pleaſing Wines by our ill Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement, or ill Keeping may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſower, and very unpleaſant. <hi>The Fear of the Lord maketh a merry Heart, and giveth Joy and Gladneſs,</hi> Ecclus 1.2. So much Religion is a thing of the nobleſt Joy, that it gives no little Joy, not only to thoſe who ſincerely Profeſs, and ſincerely Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice it themſelves; but even to thoſe who behold it, when thus Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs'd and Practiced, in others. I am ſure the thing which is very delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in its Nature, much more is made ſo by your Ladyſhip; Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on has often appeared to me as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a particular and ſurprizing De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, when I have beheld it in your Deportment. The <hi>French</hi> Philoſopher told one of your Sex, that no Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty was equal to that of Truth, and the Writer of his Life makes this Remark, that the Saying was no
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:103318:15"/>Complement, and he talked more like a Philoſopher than a Courtier. I am ſure, this ſaying, that the Beauty of Virtue is above all other, can be no Affront to a Perſon, who has a large ſhare of Virtue, and ſo in the Praiſes of it. There was a Sect of Philoſophers, which ſo many of the Noble Youth reſorted to in the Time of <hi>Epicus,</hi> as to a Court, and which pretended to all the Art<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Refinement of Wit; but here their Wit did not ſhew it ſelf, nor do them Service, when they profeſs'd the Study and Advancement of Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and yet admitted not any ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled thought of Religion into their Debates upon it: The <hi>Epicureans</hi> purſuing Pleaſure, and not carrying this along with them, went out of their way all the time, and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Men, the farther ſtill they went, ſtill were farther off from Pleaſure, and when there was ſo much of the Name in their Books and Harangues, there was little of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:103318:15"/>the thing in their Mind or Condition. It is the end of a Man, of a wiſe Man ſo to order every thing, that he may find a Pleaſure in every thing he does, in all things belonging to him: A wiſe Man he cannot be, he has no true Light in his Mind, who with all his buſie ſearch can think of fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Pleaſure by any other Light then that of Religion. May every thing your Ladyſhip does entertain you with Joy, eſpecially Religion, and this ſo much more, becauſe this will give an high taſt of Joy to all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things. The chief delight of Piety is in it ſelf a Delight of the Mind, and not therefore leſs, the Pleaſures of the Mind are the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt: But indeed, that the Mind may be capable of the Religious Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, it muſt be prepared with a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Frame of Spirit, a true and ſuitable Diſpoſition towards it, as the Body it ſelf his very little Senſe of bodily Enjoyments, if Indiſpoſed. Some complain they find not that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:103318:16"/>lofty Satisfaction, that Rapture we talk of: But we never ſaid, there was ſuch a Delight, unleſs upon a moſt hearty Tryal, and Religion is not therefore to be blamed, becauſe they are very Blameable; nor is there any want in Religion, becauſe they never found what they never ſought.</p>
            <p>May your Ladyſhip find a Joy in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Act of Religion, eſpecially in Prayer, which procures ſtrength for the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the other Acts thereof, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of Satisfaction in the doing them, and which is it ſelf ſo plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, that it has a foretaſt of Heaven, where is fulneſs of Joy and Pleaſure for evermore. Well may Prayer give us a foretaſt of Heaven, ſeeing it carries us thither every time we Pray as when St. <hi>Paul</hi> was caught up into the third Heaven; he not only heard the words which are not to be uttered, but perhaps he taſted the Enjoyments which are not to be conceived. Prayer carries us up to Heaven, and then in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:103318:16"/>(as Angels do to thoſe, to whom they give a friendly Convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance) it ſets us down again gently up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Earth, and makes Earth it ſelf more pleaſant, when thus it has brought us back from Heaven: The Man who goes ſo often thither, muſt needs return with ſomething of the Pleaſures, and the Riches of the Place, as the Merchant, who Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels often to the Countrey of Gold and Silver, and precious Stones, does as often bring from thence ſome of the gaudy, and admired, and dazling Goods.</p>
            <p>That you may be prepared for the devout Offices of Prayer, and for all the exalted Satisfactions of it, be pleaſed to compoſe that Mind, which indeed is ſeldom diſcompoſed, to fix your Soul for an Attention to the pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Work, and ſo God himſelf will attend, and have a kind regard to the Work, and to the Perſon. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you begin to Pray, you may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare and fix your Mind by ſome good
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:103318:17"/>Thoughts, as ſhort as may be, of the Duty you are undertaking, and of the God you are to Addreſs to in the Duty, and caſt off for the Time all your common Thoughts of worldly Things, that you may think more, and better of the Duty, and of God. Your Thoughts are always harmleſs, but they may not ſo eaſily be always uſeful, nor always Pious in that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Elevation, when they are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed upon worldly Things, they are formed and faſhioned for the time into a likeneſs with them; your Mind then complies and condeſcends to an unaffected Debaſement, it ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits and bows down, with a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Regret, to the Meanneſs of the Subject; as the Eagle, with all its greatneſs, and lofty Flights, vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafes ſometimes to lower it ſelf and come down, when its Quarry is near the Earth. As to the Work you are to undertake in Praying, you may be pleaſed to conſider, that you intend to ask Bleſſings for Soul and Body,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:103318:17"/>and particular Bleſſings; ſuch, and ſuch things for both; and you may conſider particularly, what things they are you intend to ask. You may not forget, that not only Prayer is a moſt holy Work, but if you would obtain what you ask, you are alſo to be Holy, before and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards: Pure Hands ſhould be lift up; if there be not Purity, there will not be Strength in thoſe Hands, nor in the Prayer. As to the God you Addreſs to in Prayer, you may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that as you are a weak and needy Creature to want the things you Pray for, ſo he is a great God, and able, a bountiful God, and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to give them: That He may be moved to give them, you are at all times, but eſpecially in the Praying time, to pay all the Reverence to your Maker, and the Maker of all the World, to Him who dwells in Heaven, and Governs on Earth; to Him who dwells in the higheſt Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, knows, and preſerves, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:103318:18"/>all things to the Ioweſt Earth. You may again conſider, that having retired from your ordinary Company, you are now to Converſe with an higher Being. Indeed the remove from our common Buſineſs and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation to Prayer is ſo great, that we cannot in ſuch a ſudden Motion, without ſome preparing Thoughts, take off our Mind from things of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Exerciſe, and place it on thoſe of Devotion: The diſtance between theſe things is ſo wide, that however Spirits are ſaid to be very nimble in their Motions, the Soul cannot paſs the next Minute from the one to the other. Nothing more apt than Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation to engage our Mind, and after the withdrawing of our Body from it, the remembrance of its Tranſactions, whether pleaſant or unpleaſant, ſeems to place us ſtill in the midſt of our Company, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain us with them: In reſpect of this Converſation, that with God is a thing altogether new, it is more
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:103318:18"/>refined and excellent, and therefore we cannot ſo very ſoon be capable of it, as he who has Converſed with Peaſants and the meaneſt Perſons, does not thus become the moſt Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh'd Man for the higher ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to the Preſence and Thrones of Princes. Very narrow and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect is all our Correſpondence with Spirits, and even with thoſe who, as ſome imagine, have a nearer Alliance to Matter, and ſo to us: Our Eyes ſees nothing, our Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings very little of them; no Senſe or Faculty is ſatisfied in the enquiry into them; whenever we perceive their being near us, we al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt covet to be farther from them, we entertain them with a Reverence very like Amazement and Horror. If our Diſadvantages be ſuch in all our Entercourſe with Spirits, much more in that with the Father of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits: And then ſhould not <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the ſofter meaning, <hi>prepare to meet his God?</hi> And thus we ſhall
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:103318:19"/>make thoſe Diſadvantages as little as may be to us; at leaſt we ſhall be ſo prepared for our attending God, as Men put on the beſt Dreſs they have, when they are to wait on Perſons much above them.</p>
            <p>I have here allowed my ſelf ſo much more enlargment on the neceſſity of forming our Minds into a ſuitable Frame, before our Praying, becauſe otherwiſe there can be little Thought in our Prayer, and leſs Affection, and the Prayer which wants either, muſt want Succeſs: Therefore is there ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Succeſs to ſo many Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; they may well not have it, when they do not deſerve it, &amp; they cannot deſerve what they ſeem not to deſire.</p>
            <p>If your other Engagements will comply with ſo many Times; let your Prayers be thrice in a Day, in the Morning the firſt Buſineſs, at Night the laſt, and at Noon before your Dinner; becauſe a Work ſo Carnal as Eating, would make
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:103318:19"/>you leſs diſpoſed for a Work ſo Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual as Praying; and becauſe this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves a place before every other Buſineſs, and it is to be our Meat thus <hi>to do the Will of Him who ſent us,</hi> and thus to pray for Grace that we may do the Will of him that ſent us into the World. Your Prayers are to be Publick and Private, not only private, but publick upon every Opportunity, not only publick, but private too, and you conſtant in the Seaſons of both. As to publick Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, the Church has preſcribed, and who has a better Right to preſcribe? Who could have better Succeſs? As to private, your own Devotion will ſoon be skilful, and the Advice of Pious Books will give you Laws: Such Laws your Books will be ready to give, and you to obey.</p>
            <p>I would adviſe your having not only particular Times, but a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Place for your Private Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſo, if the Place be not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved for this uſe alone, yet the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:103318:20"/>Duty it ſelf ſhould be alway perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in that place, reſerved for that alone: Then as often as you come near this Religious Apartment, ſome good Thought will come near you too, when you ſhall remember the Buſineſs you have there often done, and you are now to do: There may well be ſome Vertue in that Air, which has been made fragrant and ſo often ſweet with the Incenſe of your Prayers.</p>
            <p>The Grace of God is the chief thing you are to pray for, becauſe all other things will follow this. You are to pray for Grace, that it may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct you in all ſuch things in which a Chriſtian is to be inſtructed, and may turn your Thoughts towards Religion, and your Inclinations to a Deſire for the Benefits thereof. You are to pray for Grace, that it may di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect and move you to enter upon a ſolemn Courſe of Religion, direct and give Strength to the whole Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of it, guard your Age ſo tender againſt the many Temptations of the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:103318:20"/>World, and fix it againſt the ſeveral Misfortunes thereof upon the true Foundations of Religion and Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and give it a true Notion of the World: Then will you know that this gaudy World is a place of Vanity, and that nothing but Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion can make it a place of Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and ſo you will know the wiſeſt thing which can be known by Man in the whole Circle of his boaſted Learning: Pity it is that we do not know it ſooner, that only many Years and many Misfortunes ſhould teach it, more Years than have yet paſt over your Head, and worſe Misfortunes then (I hope) will ever come near your Condition; though indeed the being above Misfortunes is not one of thoſe peculiar Privile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges belonging to Birth and Quality. Let my Experience be yours, let not this be one of the dear bought things your Sex is ſaid to covet: But as the Complaiſance of our Sex delights to preſent coſtly things to yours, may the Experience be purchaſed only
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:103318:21"/>at my Coſt, and teach us both. And as the Gallantry of our Sex very often expoſes it ſelf for the Safety and the Intereſt of yours, ſo let the Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and the Evil be only mine.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Dear bought Experience taught me what it true,</l>
               <l>And Friendſhip bids me tell that Truth to you.</l>
            </q>
            <p>You are to pray for Grace, that it may now betimes prevent your be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing guilty of thoſe Sins, which many young Perſons begin too ſoon to be guilty of and which ſooner or later are to have a Repentance, and the Repentance is to have ſo much coſt, in Tears and Sighs, in painful Thought and unpleaſant Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance: Surely thoſe Sins are Diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the moſt Dangerous Kind, which we ſhould rather chuſe to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent then to remove, and when they have entertainment from our Youth, they are like that forward Fruit which is very unwholſome and will ſoon be rotten. You are to pray for Grace, that it may guide you through this Life to a better; as hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py as I wiſh your preſent Life, there is yet one far more happy, which I
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:103318:21"/>doubt not, you wiſh your ſelf; and which that Grace is to guide you to, and moreover it is to guide you through the ſeveral parts of your preſent Life with all the Succeſs and Bleſſing in all the Management of it. As you are to pray for your ſelf, ſo for thoſe next to your ſelf, your near Relations, and for all good things to them, Spiritual and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral. The Advice you are ready to prevent, becauſe the Office, I know, is very pleaſing to you, who pay ſo much Duty, where you ow it, and ſo much Love to your other Relations, more (I had almoſt ſaid) than you can be ſuppoſed to owe. You are not only to pray for what you want, but to give thanks for your not hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wanted many things, for thoſe you have enjoyed from the firſt day of your Life unto this, for your Noble Birth, and wealthy Fortune, and Virtuous Education. Such a Thankſgiving to God will require a Prayer to him for all the Endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Mind ſuitable to ſuch a
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:103318:22"/>Birth, and Fortune and Education, and for the making theſe his Favours uſeful to the Glory of him you pray to; and him who gave them. You are to pray for a low Opinion of all this World, and of one part of it more than all, of your ſelf, that <hi>your heart may not be haughty, nor your Eyes lofty, and you may not exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe your ſelf in great matters, nor in things too high for you,</hi> Moreover you may pray, that to your other, to your many earthly Goods may be added that of Health, in order to your being more capable of making the beſt uſe of all, your doing more ſervice to God, more good to others. You may pray that in this your <hi>walking through the Vally of the Shadow of Death God would make you to fear no Evil, and make his Goodneſs and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to follow you all the Days of your Life, that ſo you may dwell in the Houſe of the Lord for ever,</hi> dwell in his Houſe here, and in that other <hi>not made with hands, eternal in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens.</hi> Your prayers upon theſe ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:103318:22"/>occaſions are to be ſhort, and then may be more ſervent, and what is wanting in length may be ſupplied in a more warm Devotion, which is to God more pleaſing; a warm Devotion more pleaſing to God, then a Burning Sacrifice. The Force of our Prayers, when more cloſe and united, in a narrower Room, in leſs Time and fewer Words, may be ſtronger, and as that Force is ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, the Prayers will be more earneſt. The Orator muſt weep himſelf, if he will be ſure to have his hearers weep: Much more we muſt be earneſt in praying if we expect that God will be moved in hearing, that he will ſhew to us a part of the ſtrange Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction he has to Mankind which the Prophets have told us of, and which only their Flights can deſcribe. It is one deſign of Prayer to unite us to God, and ſo much it does unite us to him, that our Affections and his are almoſt to the ſame; as we are affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted more or leſs in the preſenting our Prayer ſo is he in the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:103318:23"/>
            <p>I pretend not here to have given all the Rules which are neceſſary for Prayer, but ſome more particular to to your Ladyſhips Quality and Age I have deſigned to give, and then to recommend your Learning of other more general Rules for Prayer and for all things from the Books of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Wiſdom, thoſe which you are not a Stranger to, and which, I am ſure, you will be every Day more acquainted with. The Books are to be few and choſen, and ſo much the rather ſhould yours be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, becauſe in every Kind you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the beſt: Few Books, that they may be read, and choſen, that the reading may be uſeful.</p>
            <p>At the ſame time you read the Writings of others, let this of all things be written upon your mind, that whereas there are ſeveral parts of Religion, the chief part is practice, and a living in obedience to the Commands of God, and that all pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:103318:23"/>to Religion is trifling with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it, and that ſtill the Older you are, the more Practice is required.</p>
            <p>In order to your being moved to live in a Religious Method of all this Practice, you may be aſſured that your Life can never be happy with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Religion, and then what is to make your whole Life happy, is to be it ſelf a greater part of it, is to be indeed begun in the firſt Seaſons of Life, and ſo continued to the laſt. If the beginning afterwards were not late and ineffectual, yet it would be leſs certain and more difficult, the beginning ſooner will by the long and early cuſtom make Religion that which I ſo much deſire it may be to you, and may be accounted by you, a delightful thing, the moſt delightful in the World. Religion I have declared before to be a thing which has all the Refinement and Delicacy of Pleaſure; and then why ſhould we loſe ſo much Pleaſure all the time we are not engaged in the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:103318:24"/>Intereſts of Religion? Youth is the time, in which we think we have a Claim to Pleaſu e; and then, if it covet all other Pleaſure, why not the trueſt and higheſt Joy, and why not Religion, which alone can give this, which alone can ſecure the other? We can no more be happy too ſoon then too much; and all the Wit and all the Power of Man cannot order an happy Life without ordering the Life to be firſt Religious.</p>
            <p>This Truth is as great as evident; O that all thoſe would conſider it, to whom the conſidering of it would be uſeful, that is, all Mankind. And ſeeing it is the Deſire of every Man to be happy, there ſhould be this o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Deſire of the Good and the Wiſe, that every Man would conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and every Man would do what is neceſſary to make him, as he deſires to be, very happy.</p>
            <p>Be pleaſed to remember that high degree in the World does not make Vertue a lower or a needleſs thing;
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:103318:24"/>and that Riches make Religion ſtill more needful, becauſe Riches have many Dangers, againſt which Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion only can give Security, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe when there is ſuch a plenty of other things, it is pity there ſhould be a want of that alone. Riches are coveted too much, Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion too little; and yet this ſhould be more deſired, if not for its own ſake, at leaſt for the ſake of Riches, which, if they are never ſo much deſired, never ſo much poſſeſt, are yet no Bleſſing without Religion. You may remember alſo that Noble Blood, a Body Highborn does not make us ſo great as that Nobler ſort of Mind, which ſhews its heavenly Birth in heavenly Actions. You may not forget that no Beauty does ſo charm, no Dreſs ſo adorn, as Vertue always does, no Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is ſo truly delightful, as a devout Communion in Gods worſhip, no Behaviour and Accompliſhment has ſo lovely a Grace, as that of Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:103318:25"/>in the Worſhip of him who cannot have too much: Happy we, if from the beſt of us he could have enough; but we muſt be contented, as God is ſatisfied, with our being <hi>Servants, though unprofitable.</hi> Noble Birth, and Beauty, the Arts of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation and Behaviour, and all the Glories of Dreſs, which are things very much admired, will deſerve much more to be ſo, when joined to Religion, and when they have the great Advantages which Religion gives them: Indeed this gives the greateſt, becauſe it is greater, it is better then all things. <hi>All the things you can deſire</hi> (or others can deſire, can Love in you) <hi>are not to be compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red unto it, the gain thereof is better than fine Gold, it is more precious than Rubies, and its ways are ways of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantneſs.</hi> So ſays <hi>Solomon,</hi> and the ſame Author ſays, a Gracious Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man retaineth Honour. He had high Birth himſelf, and ſo much of it, that the Haughty <hi>Aethiopian</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:103318:25"/>Emperors; amongſt all their Bulky and noiſie Titles, are proud of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more then that they have (as they pretend) Royal Blood flowing from him. <hi>Solomon</hi> had a King his Father, and his Father the chief Head of a Family of Kings, the firſt and laſt ſettled Royal Family in <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el; Solomon</hi> was a King himſelf, and as he had Riches and Greatneſs, to make him awfull, ſo he had Beauty and Wiſdom, and all the Charms of Wit and Converſation and Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage to make him lovely to Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind: <hi>Grace was poured into his Lips, and he was fairer then the Children of Men, he dwelt in Ivory Palaces, and his Garments were perfumed with Myrrhe and Aloes and Caſſia, and Kings-Daughters were among his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Women.</hi> In the ſame Pſalm his Queen too is deſcribed, and in vain had <hi>ſhe been brought unto the King in Raiment of Needlework,</hi> and in vain <hi>ſhe had ſtood at his right hand in Gold of Ophir, and her cloathing of wrought
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:103318:26"/>Gold,</hi> if ſhe the Daughter as well as Wife of a King had not been <hi>all glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious within</hi> as well as ſhe was with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out in all her Aegyptian Glory; the King would never have ſo much <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired her Beauty, if ſhe had not heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and conſidered, enclined her Ear and Worſhipt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Writer of your Sex brings in the Shepherd profeſſing all the Rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Eſteem, and ſomething more the Paſſion to the Sheperdels, not for thoſe Endowments, which are commonly treated with all the ſofter Language and reſpectful Names, but for other and greater things.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Yet not for theſe do I</hi> Alinda <hi>Love,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hear then what 'tis that does my Paſſion move:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That thou ſtill earlieſt at the Temple art</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And ſtill the laſt that does from thence depart,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Pan<hi>'s Altar is by thee the ofineſt preſt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thine's ſtill the faireſt Offering and the beſt;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And all thy other Action ſeem to be</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The true Reſult of unfeign d Piety.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>Theſe Perfections ſhined through all the ſhade of that Meaneſs which Poetry had dreſt her in, and her own Humility was ready to put on; and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:103318:26"/>they diſcover'd to every admiring Eye the Noble Lady (for ſo ſhe was) under the borrowed Diſguiſe of a Shepher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſs.</p>
            <p>I have ſpoken ſo much more upon Noble Birth, becauſe as that is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great Bleſſing in it ſelf, ſo it has been to ſome a very great Evil, to thoſe who have ſo valued them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or have been taught by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, attending them, ſo to value themſeves upon it, as to imagine they wanted nothing elſe, and were above the being good, above that very thing which would make them ſtill more Noble, and would give them an higher Rank then Birth had given them, would place them above all things beſides it ſelf. I have all the high regard to Noble Birth, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to that which your Ladyſhip de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rives from a Family I have ſo peculiar an Honour for: I would only adviſe all Perſons who are born in Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs not to have too high a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard for it in one Sence, and ſcarce high enough in another. The gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:103318:27"/>Precept of the Philoſopher ſeems to be particular to them in its de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, that <hi>men ſhould reverence them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves:</hi> Surely they ſhould teach o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to pay Honour to them by do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Honour to themſelves, they ſhould have a Reverence for the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories and the Venerable Ghoſts of their Anceſtors, in not embezzling the Honour as well as the Eſtate which they bequeathed, and in act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo that their Aſhes may not be diſturbed, nor they dead once more in thoſe whom they left behind to repreſent them. Vertue did firſt give Honour and Title; and that is ſtill neceſſary to preſerve it. Honour acquired by Virtue is greater than that of Inheritance, and when the Honour which was firſt the Reward of Vertue is carried down to others as the Gift of Inheritance, theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed are Noble once, the firſt Day of their Birth: But, if they continue and enlarge thoſe vertuous Actions
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:103318:27"/>of their Anceſtors, they make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Noble anew, every Day of their Life, confirm and enlarge their original Right to the Honour they received from others, and then begin to make it their own. <hi>Jehu</hi> could not chuſe but pay a regard to Birth, in the midſt of all his Holy Rage, and the Wickedneſs of <hi>Jezebel,</hi> in whom there was but one thing to give her any claim to a regard, and for the ſake of that one thing ſhe had it, ſhe was to ſuffer leſs Diſhonour in her Death, becauſe ſhe had ſo much honour in her Birth, <hi>Go, bury her, for ſhe is a Kings Daughter.</hi> The Son of God, who vouchſafed to be born, as Man, in all the Forms of Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, choſe a Noble mans Daughter for the Subject of a Miracle to raiſe her when dead, and ſo a Noblemans Son, to reſcue him from Death. I have not deſigned one word to leſſen Birth, but all to make it greater, by Vertue added to it, and adorning it.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:103318:28"/>
            <p>With the ſame deſign I have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of Riches and Pleaſures, and all the deſirable Advantages of the World, and which are only of this World: I would not have them excluded, I would have thoſe who poſſeſs them not to love them better than themſelves, and not to exclude Religion, and then Happineſs too, which never goes in to any Place, but where Religion goes in before it. The Things of the World have too much wrought on many Aged, and not Imprudent Perſons: Much more then is there need of Caution to one of your Age, and your Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, when too many of the ſame greater Figure have abuſed their worldly Advantages, being firſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed themſelves by the ill Counſels of thoſe who have been too near them. Indeed your Ladyſhip gives me no occaſion to ſuſpect that you had ever any to Miſguide you, or that you are to be Miſguided, when I by a delightful Experience have
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:103318:28"/>viewed ſo much Virtue, as ſhould either make me think you had never been attacked by ill Counſels, or you had always Virtue, Strong and Wiſe, to conquer them. There are Perſons in the World, (and may you be always one of thoſe) upon whom Ill Advice is no leſs ineffectual then Good is very often on others, ill things cannot ſtand before them, and, as no venemous Beaſt can live in ſome Climates, they dye as ſoon as they come near them, or within the fatal Air of this ſo mighty Innocence. There is a Serpent to every Daughter of <hi>Eve,</hi> as well as there was to <hi>Eve</hi> her ſelf, and ſo to every Son of <hi>Adam:</hi> But however the Serpent be <hi>more ſubtle then any Beaſt of the Field,</hi> there are thoſe who will be innocent, be he never ſo Crafty, and they will not <hi>eat of the Fruit,</hi> and without eating of it <hi>their Eyes are opened, and they know Good and Evil,</hi> and ſo as to purſue, and to avoid. Every good Perſon
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:103318:29"/>has ſomething of an Exorciſt, in him the Apoſtolical Power of caſting out Devils is hot loſt, to him it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, the evil Spirit cannot bear his Preſence, as he could not bear that of Chriſt, when he ſell down before him, and cried out, <hi>I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee torment me not.</hi> Beſides the many Temptations from others, there is a Tempter within our ſelves, there is a Principle of Vanity in the Nature of Man, in this too earthly Nature, which carries us on to theſe Vain Earthly Things with a fierce Deſire, as fierce alas, as if they were not Vain: From this Principle, which ſeems to be almoſt as old as our Nature, riſe all the Sins of our following Life, theſe are only ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny irregular ways into which our Inclinations divide themſelves for the Purſuit of earthly Things. From this Principle of Corruption in our Souls, riſe all our Sins, as from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of natural Corruption in our Bodies do riſe the ſeveral Diſeaſes of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:103318:29"/>them. The beſt of us therefore may have need to be upon our Guard a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Things of the World, and good Reaſon there is to keep low, and to correct betimes that prevailing Cauſe of Corruption by Advice, and by Endeavour.</p>
            <p>In order to your ſucceſsful Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs in this Courſe of Religion, you will, (I am ſure) be eaſily, and ſoon Exhorted to have (ſhall I ſay?) Or to continue a ſuitable and devout Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to that Day of the Week, which is particularly deſigned for Religious Offices. The Day, which is ſet apart, and for ſomething, and that can be no other than holy Duty; the Day, which we call the Lord's Day in a prophane Jeſt, if we do not keep it to the Lord, if our uſe of it be Prophane, that is, not Religious. <hi>He who regardeth a Day, regardeth it unto the Lord. Man is Born to La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,</hi> (as <hi>Job</hi> has told us) he is deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by God to be always in Action, and that Action as much as may be
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:103318:30"/>worthy of himſelf, and uſeful to himſelf, or others: They who have the loweſt Reſpect for this Day, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend not then to do the Buſineſs of their particular Calling; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhould they not do that of their general Calling, as they are Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans? This one Day was not ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, only to be a Blank, a void Space in our Time, and to have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing written upon it: If we could be contented to loſe one Day, as to our own Intereſt, in every Week of ſo ſhort a Life, yet God is not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to allow the loſs of one, as to his Service, we complain, ſays a Learned <hi>Heathen,</hi> that Life is ſhort, and Time is ſwift, and yet like Men, very Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrifty, and very Poor, we miſpend our too little time, as if we had too much. Whatever time we miſpend, we ſhould take care, like Men luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in their Expences, and yet ſtill juſt in ther Principles, to miſpend none but our own Indeed,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:103318:30"/>if we ſhould take this Care, we ſhould miſpend no Time, becauſe none is ours, much leſs that which God has made His more than any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, His in a peculiar manner: Not only God, but Man; all the Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Man, that of the Church, and that of the State has made it God's own Time: And if any Sacred Thing, which one Man gave to God, another cannot take away but with the blackeſt Guilt, much leſs that which God has given to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and Man gave to God. Our u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing well this part of our Time will prevent our abuſing every other part, becauſe it will advance us to ſuch a State of Mind, it will lead us into ſuch Rules of Life, that we ſhall learn to be always careful, and reſolve to be always good. Surely we ſhall be ſo, if we remember an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles Saying, <hi>that we are not our own;</hi> and then not our Time; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe if we our ſelves are not our own, then not any thing belonging
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:103318:31"/>to us, which can be held no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than our Being is, and muſt paſs over with our ſelves to the great So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign Lord.</p>
            <p>You are ready, (I know) to keep this Day with all the ſolemn Care, and you are to perform the Duties of it with all the ſolemn Reverence. The fix'd and ordinary Duties of it are Praying, and Hearing, Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Reading, and Acts of Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and moreover there is an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Duty, the receiving the Sacrament of the Lord's Supper, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your Years now meet, and come up to your devout Inclinations, and Time now almoſt overtakes your Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety and Prudence, which (as ſwift as Time is) have been ſo much before it. Since this is ſo great which now we ſee, how great muſt that be, which we may expect; the good Things we view at a diſtance, though ſo far off, yet appear not little, they already entertain our Eyes with a pleaſing Proſpect, and fill our Minds
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:103318:31"/>with amuſing Thought and the brighteſt Image, when we look forward to the Seaſons of full and ripe Perfection, of which we have the firſt Fruits now already. That the Sacrament of Perfection may give you a large ſhare thereof, and haſten it upon you, and ſo gratify your eager Zeal and our ſwelling Expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, you will not fail to receive the Sacrament as often as you have Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to receive it. No mean believe me, between not receiving, and refuſing; if you do not receive it, you refuſe it; and be pleaſed to conſider how heinous the Crime muſt be to refuſe, when God does offer, not to come, when God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites. Every time the Sacrament is to be adminiſtred, it is offered to all the Perſons of the Place, as much to each of them, as if it were offered in expreſs words, and by name to every ſingle Perſon only and not to the reſt, for him only provided. And then you may begin to think how conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:103318:32"/>a thing it is for a great Man, for one much greater than our ſelves to order a particular entertainment for us, and how indecent a thing to deny our Preſence.</p>
            <p>That you may hereafter receive this Sacrament with advantage, and now perform with advantage the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Duties of Worſhip, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready you are not more capable of then zealous for, I would propoſe few things more and ſooner than a Conſtancy to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in which the Performance of all thoſe Duties is ſo ſtrictly required, and the manner of performing them ſo well preſcribed. A Church it is, which cannot fail to be agreeable to you, becauſe it ſo well inſtructs you in Religion, in no part whereof you would be ignorant, it is ſo ready to promote your Knowledge in every part, which you are ſo eager to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove: A Church, which the more you underſtand, is ſtill the better ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, and her Satisfaction is ſtill
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:103318:32"/>made greater by yours, inſtead of envying you your own Knowledge, or denying you a ſhare in that of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers by Inſtruction. I would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend a Conſtancy to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the Church with full Judgment of your Mind, and ſincere Good-will of your Soul, that Soul, which is to have ſo much Advantage from that Communion. When I give this Advice, I offer it with all the Sincerity which becomes the Subject of Advice, Religion, and which becomes a Man who has all the Zeal for the well-being of the Perſon to whom he offers it, for this well-being in every thing, eſpecially in Religion. I would be ſure to be thus ſincere, when I propoſe this (I am ſure) wholſome Counſel, and therefore in that very Inſtant I for the time endeavour to forget my own being a Member of this Church, I ſeparate in my Thoughts my being ſo from my Advice to you to be ſo forever. I do not exhort you to this
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:103318:33"/>Communion, becauſe I live within it, but becauſe it is the beſt for your Eternal Welfare, and for my own. And ſo I am not partial to my ſelf in my inviting you to my own Church, as ſome are fond of every thing they meet with at their own Houſe. But I ſhould be indeed very partial, if I ſhould reſerve good things to my ſelf, if I ſhould not exhort you to a Communion with that Church, which is, and which upon all my Experience and all my Conſideration I have found to be the beſt, and which I therefore choſe at firſt, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now continue in. As Chriſt's Diſciples ſaid upon a like occaſion, <hi>Whither ſhall we go?</hi> So may I ſay, if we are not to continue in this Church, to what other ſhall we go? What neceſſary thing for the Souls of Men can any other give, which we have not here? Surely if Men will be hearty in any Religion, they will not fail of embracing ours, when they have heartily enquired
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:103318:33"/>what it is, and they truly know, how much it deſerves to be embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. Therefore perhaps ſo many Atheiſts oppoſe our Church with a particular Fury, and ſo many, when they have revolted from it, have ſoon become Atheiſts afterwards, their denying all Religion has been the next Step to the denying one, of which a leſs thing can ſcarce be ſaid, then that is as good as any. Others going from it have indeed not known whither to go, they have roved a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout in a Circle of Error, have gon backward and forward in an endleſs Maze of Religions, and whereas once there was a Promiſe <hi>to move the Earth,</hi> if there were but found <hi>a Place to ſtand on,</hi> the Religious world turns round with them, becauſe they have not ſuch a place. When <hi>Cain went out from the Preſence of the Lord, he became a Fugitive and a Vagabond in the Earth, and his Puniſhment</hi> in this Senſe too <hi>was greater than he could bear:</hi> The Spirits of ill Men
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:103318:34"/>ſome imagin to have their wandring in the air for a part of Puniſhment, the worſt of Spirits and the Prince of the Air gave this Account of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that <hi>he went to and fro in the Earth, and walkt up and down in it.</hi> So the departing from our Church has been puniſht in many with their being never fixt, who would not be fixt where they might, where they ſhould have been very ſteady. Never indeed ſhall they find the Truth, who are alway ſeeking, and will never believe, they have found it, as they cannot be long in a right way, who will change their way every Minute and every ſtep. The purſuing as well as the renouncing every Religion is an ill extream; the ſeeking thus for ever is one ill ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream as well as the not ſeeking any is another. There can be no reaſon at any time to forſake our Church; no reaſon to be always forſaking one, and running into another.</p>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:103318:34"/>
            <p>I inſiſt ſo much more on this Plea for our Communion, not only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Subject is very pleaſing to my ſelf, but alſo very advantagious it is to you. Indeed to your thoughts of this beſt Church I would give the beſt Impreſſions, that you might be above the Danger of receiving any of the worſe kind hereafter, that you might be fixt before at this your Age, which is ſo capable of Good, and ſo liable to Ill, and beſides the Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of your Age there is the Softneſs of your Sex to make you the more diſpoſed for the taking of any ſort of Stamp or Impreſſion. You will for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give this my troubleſome, however zealous, Induſtry to ſee you ſettled in true Principles, and in ſtrong con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction of that Truth, becauſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtancy (as you read before) in Religion is a thing ſo Dangerous, and Conſtancy in a falſe one is a thing ſo fatal.</p>
            <p>Moreover Attempts have been ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry often made upon thoſe of juſt
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:103318:35"/>Sex for the betraying of them into a falſe Religion, and too often thoſe at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts have bin ſucceſsful. My deſires are ſo much more importunate for your continuing in a Religion (which has ſo much reaſon for it) in a good Religion upon very good Reaſon, becauſe they who at firſt took Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion by that handle, and afterwards held it there are ſaid in Scripture to be Noble; the doing ſo was a mark of a Generous Spirit, and ſuch a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is very ſuitable to ſuch a Quality as yours, and no leſs ſuitable to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
            <p>Many are the Arguments I could urge to prove the Neceſſity and the Advantage of your being a Daughter of the Church, as well as of your No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Parents. But all ſuch Arguments would as much be loſt upon you, who have little need to be convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, as they are too often upon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in a worſe Sence, who reſolve not to be ſo. I ſhall offer no more
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:103318:35"/>Arguments, then two, and thoſe, as very peculiar to your Quality and more exalted State: one I borrow from him who had no ſuch Zeal for the Church as ſhould make him par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial to it, but approaching Death, which makes ſo many wiſe, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſincere, taught him to confeſs, <hi>that the People of England being natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally inclined to Freedom, and bred in Riches and Plenty can hardly be indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to embrace any Religious Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline which may abridg their Liberty, and Pleaſures:</hi> That is, any other Diſcipline then this of the Church, which at the ſame Time it allows us Liberty and Riches and Pleaſures, does prefcribe our not abuſing them to our own greateſt Diſadvantage, and moreover our uſing them to the Advantage of others, and of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. I now may add my other Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, the Order and Decency of our Worſhip, which makes it very natural to Perſons of your Nobler
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:103318:36"/>Rank, who are diſtinguiſhed from others by order (that of High and Low in the different Figures of the World) and by Decency, their having ſo much of it in their appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance: They have all the Forms of Addreſs paid to them, wherever they vouchſafe to appear, and therefore ſomething is to be paid by them to <hi>the Prince of the Kings of the Earth.</hi> So K. <hi>David</hi> argued, and that gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Devotion, which was ſo much his Vertue and his Glory, made him, apt to argue, <hi>See now I dwell in a houſe of Cedar, and the Ark of God dwelleth within Curtains. And ſo God himſelf did argue, offer it now unto thy Prince, will he be pleaſed with thee, or accept thy Perſon?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From this my naming of order in Worſhip I will take occaſion to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend it in all other things: And ſo much rather, becauſe if there be a Rule for all other things, much more will there be one for
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:103318:36"/>Religion, and when all things are done in order, they will be done with eaſe, and be finiſh't each of them in very good time, and ſo there will not be a want of time, and a want of Thought free and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>engaged, for Prayer and other Works of Religion. To do things in order, even thoſe of our Buſie and common Life, is ſo far a part of Religion, as we thus imitate God, who <hi>is not the Author of Confuſion,</hi> who made, and who preſerves all things ſtill, <hi>in number weight and meaſure,</hi> who has fixt the times for Night and Day, for Summer and Winter, and for every thing, who has taught thoſe Creatures Order which know little elſe: <hi>He hath appointed the Men for Seaſons, and the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> knoweth his going down, the Stork in the Heaven knoweth her appointed Time, and the Turtle and the Cra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, and the Swallow obſerve the time of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> That Wiſdom of <hi>Solution,</hi> the Fame whereof was in all Nations rou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:103318:37"/>bout, not only ſhewed it ſelf in Reigning ſo as that <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> dwelt ſafely, every Man under his Vine, and under his Fig-tree; not only in ſpeaking Three Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Proverbs, and in ſpeaking of Trees, and Beaſts, and Fowl; his Wiſdom alſo appeared in the Order of his private Buſineſs, that of his Family, and the Queen of <hi>Sheba</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired it in this Order, as well as in greater Things. His Wiſdom taught him to preſcribe, as always to himſelf, ſo to others fix'd Times for all things, and then to declare that, <hi>To every thing there is a Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and a Time to every purpoſe under Heaven.</hi> But here ſome may be ready to ſay, that when each Affair is performed in all this Method, and at allotted Times, the Man becomes a Slave (and no worſe Slave then he who is his own) the Rule is a Chain, and Life is a Toil, as he who obſerves the ſtrict Rules of Phyſick is very far from being happy, or being eaſie. I
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:103318:37"/>intend not the obſerving of Order with this Anxious Care, and as if the thing muſt be done in this very man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and not otherwiſe, whatever happens, but only that it be for the moſt part obſerved, and when it may be ſo with little trouble, and with the common Foreſight of every prudent Perſon; and then there will be ſomething of Order, even in the not obſerving of it. Otherwiſe Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der would be a thing too Nice for the State of Man, as ſome things are too fine to be uſed, or to laſt. Our preſent State will not be ſo regular as a good Man would have it, nor ſo Uniform; and all of a piece, and colour, as a wiſe Man would make it, our whole Condition, when on Earth, is uneven, like the Earth it ſelf, which is divided into Hills and Plains, and rough Way as well as ſmooth. No Rule of Acting can pretend to a greater Name than that of a Law, nor to greater Authority;
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:103318:38"/>and ſeeing we live not under <hi>Perſian</hi> Emperors, every Law upon a new Over-ruling Occaſion may be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed, or be Suſpended. Order is not to be Superſtition and Caprice, like that of the Orator, who made uſe of his angry Eloquence in a Law-Suit, Commenced againſt the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Roman that ruffled and diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed his Gown. We are not to be Martyrs for our Rule, as the Man in the <hi>Greecian</hi> Common-wealth was to die for the new Law which he propoſed; and we are not to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Rules of our appointed Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, as a Pedant thoſe of his Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar, or as a Monk profeſſes to obſerve thoſe of his Society. Living in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, without the Severity of living thus, will be ſo far from being a Toyl, that it will make every thing elſe to ceaſe from being ſo; there will be Eaſe in every Buſineſs, and the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt in the Mind; when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is no Hurry without, there will be none within. Not only Uſe will
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:103318:38"/>make Order ſo familiar, but it will make it ſelf ſo pleaſant, that we ſhall not be afraid of it, we ſhall chooſe and covet it, as we chooſe the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling in an open Road, and find it much more eaſie, and we covet the Sayling by a Compaſs, and find it much more ſafe. Indeed a Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian of elder Times preſcribed this Rule of Health, <hi>that none ſhould be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved:</hi> But if none, then not his own, and then not his againſt every Rule.</p>
            <p>That the Order, which I know to be ſo uſeful in all our Life, and to be ſo needful in the beſt part of Life, in Religion, you may be ſure to obſerve in this better part; when you enter upon any Action, conſider, firſt, whether the thing you would do be Lawful, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God has not forbidden it, and whether the beſt, and the wiſeſt Men would not forbid it, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe againſt it. Very great Reaſon there is to conſider thus, becauſe you will otherwiſe have no Bleſſing
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:103318:39"/>from that God, from whom, I hope, you will have an overflowing Plenty of it; no Bleſſing ſo as to finiſh the Action you begin, or no Bleſſing af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, ſo as to have any good Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect riſing from it: And ſurely all that Prudence, which your preſent Behaviour gives us a Promiſe of, will not give you leave to think of doing any one thing in vain, much leſs that which ſhould be worſe than Vain, ſhould be hurtful. Be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to conſider firſt, whether the Thing have any ſinful part, and not firſt, what Pleaſure it may have, and what Profit; becauſe our greateſt Profit is in Religion, and in Religion ſhould be our greateſt Pleaſure; and becauſe Religion ſhould be the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning Principle of all our Actions, and ſhould be always at the Helm to guide them, and is always the moſt faithful Oracle to be conſulted upon the Iſſues of them. So a great Man ſays, a Prince, as Pious as Great, <hi>I have ſet the Lord always before me,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:103318:39"/>therefore I ſhall not be moved,</hi> Pſalms 16. I ſhall neither do, nor ſuffer Ill, I ſhall be ſure in my Actions, and ſafe in my whole Condition. The not conſidering in our firſt Steps of Action, whether it be ſuch as we ſhould go any farther in it, whether it be good or not, is an ill Thing it ſelf, much worſe than at firſt ſight it ſeems to be, it leads us into Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneneſs, and a Contempt of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; and therefore in Scripture it is a Mark hereof: Indeed ſo much rather it is a Mark of Profaneneſs; becauſe this very thing is a firſt Principle of Religion, that our Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſhould begin from Him, from whom all Creatures had their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, and becauſe, if Religion does not come in at firſt, it comes in ſeldom afterwards; either that withdraws upon the contempt, or we make the firſt contempt greater ſtill, and we harden'd Men too ſoon learn to forget what before too bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we had deſpiſed. The Action be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:103318:40"/>in diſorder, which gives the firſt place to Profit or Pleaſure, and it cannot but end as it began.</p>
            <p>Remember always your Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, that is, this your Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of your ſelf to God (as the Jews had an yearly Remembrance of the Dedication of the Temple) your taking the Vow upon your ſelf which in your Baptiſm you made by others; and that you always may remember it, be pleaſed to read the Form of Confirmation once every Quarter of the Year. This was a Sacred tye, and the firſt with which you by your own act bound the firſt and tender part of your Life, and, I know, the Bond was not uneaſie or too ſtiff for the tenderneſs of it, but, in <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Language, <hi>an Ornament of Grace unto your Head, and a Chain about your neck; and to be bound con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually upon your heart.</hi> This was one of the moſt awful, the greateſt Acts of Religion, you ever yet per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:103318:40"/>becauſe it was the ſealing of a Covenant between God and your ſelf in moſt awful manner, the Covenant made in Baptiſm, but ſeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Confirmation. You then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared what you would do, and you obliged your ſelf to the doing of it in your whole following life, and the Biſhop declared what God would do at the ſame time he prayed to God for it, that he would aſſiſt you in, and reward you for the performing your pious part. How great and ſolemn was the Engagement, when the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop askt you with others, <hi>Do ye here in the preſence of God and of this Congregation renew the ſolemn Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe and Vow that was made in your Name at your Baptiſm, ratifying and confirming the ſame in your own Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and acknowledging your ſelves bound to believe and to do all thoſe things which your Godfathers and Godmothers then undertook for you.</hi> How great and ſolemn was the Biſhops Prayer, when the Venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:103318:41"/>Man inveſted with heavenly Power, and with all things to give commanding Authority to his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and a Religious Grandeur to the performance, laid his hand up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you; as if he would convey a part of that <hi>precious ſpiritual Oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> which had been poured on his Head, to yours, like <hi>the Oyl running down from</hi> Aaron<hi>'s head,</hi> and ſo ſpreading farther to the parts below. At the ſame time the Biſhop laid one hand upon your Head, he lift up another to that Heaven from whence his Power was derived, in Prayer for you, <hi>Defend, O Lord, this thy Servant with thy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Grace, that ſhe may continue thine for ever, and daily encreaſe in thy Holy Spirit more and more; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til ſhe come into thy everlaſting King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Amen.</hi> I have indeed a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular reaſon for recommending all the nice and ſerious reſpects to your Confirmation, not only becauſe of
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:103318:41"/>the uſeful Greatneſs of the thing it<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but alſo becauſe of the extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary regard I ow it, as well as you, ſeeing I bore a part therein, had the Honour to attend you in it, and preſent you to it.</p>
            <p>My Lord your Father, as he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved me to be always, ſo upon this occaſion ſave me to be moſt particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly concerned for your Spiritual Intereſts, he did me the Honour to think favourably of me, and was willing to believe that this my zeal (for your Confirmation) had a <hi>Knowledg</hi> with it, and at the ſame time to wiſh (I may ſuppoſe) that in order to the having ſuch a Zeal, others might have ſuch a <hi>Knowledge,</hi> and therefore he askt me what Proof I had from Scripture for the practice of Confirmation: My Anſwer was to this purpoſe, that 1. however it is Sacrament to ſome, it is not to us, but indeed it follows one, and being not eſſential, but very uſeful in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, like many other uſeful and
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:103318:42"/>yet not abſolutely neceſſary things, it might not be expreſly comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and not ſo expreſly found in Scripture, which is a particular and a ſtanding Rule only for things ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely neceſſary to Salvation. In other things the Church may know that they advance the great ends of Religion, and then it wants for their uſe no other Command be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides its own. But 2dly. Confirmation has a proof from Scripture, <hi>Acts</hi> 8. <hi>The firſt Chriſtians of Samaria were ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptized upon the preaching of Philip,</hi> v. 12, <hi>and after their Baptiſm the Apoſtles ſent Peter and Johh to pray for them that they might receive the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> v. 14.15. <hi>then laid they their hands on them, and they received the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> v. 17. <hi>that is, were Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your Baptiſm placed you in the Chriſtian Church; but your being there was declared, and you engaged your ſelf to the abiding there, in
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:103318:42"/>your Confirmation: As an Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour may be ſometime un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known in the Kingdom he is ſent to, but he is not ſuppoſed, or decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to be there, till his publick En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and then he begins publick Action. When you were to be Confirmed, your Age made your beginning of Religious Action very ſeaſonable, and your Confirmation made your going on therein very neceſſary, has given it all the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Circumſtances. Go on there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as you have begun, and do, as you are obliged, and <hi>go forth in the ſtrength of the Lord God,</hi> and pray for a double Portion of that his Strength, and ſay; Give me, O my God, a zealous and ſteady Piety, a moſt devout and flaming Love of thee, O my Creatour, whom I ought to <hi>remember now in the Days of my Youth,</hi> and the Days of my Pleaſure, and I am alſo to remember thoſe other <hi>Evil Days,</hi> which as far they are from me now, yet <hi>will
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:103318:43"/>come, and the years will draw nigh, in which I ſhall ſay I have no Pleaſure.</hi> So ſhall your Confirmation be repeated upon you from God every day of your Life, and, in the Strength he gives, you ſhall become great in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and go ſo far therein, as only thoſe have gone, whoſe ſhining Example was a Light in your way, and taught you to go forth betimes, as they did before you, and as too few do after them. Our Virtue and our Age, in the common View of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, paſs through the ſame degrees, and their Progreſs often is the ſame, as there is not ripe and well grown Fruit without a Bloom before, which pleaſes ſo much at preſent, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes ſo much hereafter. We have often had a ſurprizing Account of ſome younger Saints, what good and excellent things they ſaid, what great and excellent things they did. Indeed we have heard won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:103318:43"/>Deſcriptions of the Vertues of the bleſſed Virgin in the firſt part of her Age, and ſo the Life of the Mother almoſt becomes as much a Miracle as the Birth of the Son: That ſuch particular relations were true we have no proof, and they have no credit; but the foundation of them is not without its truth, that ſhe whoſe Piety was ſo eminent af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, it is moſt likely, could never have attained thoſe glorious improvements, without beginning ſooner than others too often do; ſhe could never have been ſo <hi>highly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured of God,</hi> if God had not been highly and early beloved of her, if ſhe had not been a Virgin as much in her Mind, as otherwiſe, if her Purity had not been great in the firſt outgoings of her Life, though her firſt Conception was not undefiled.</p>
            <p>Your Confirmation leads you to Prayer, becauſe you are afterwards to beg Grace of God for your being able to anſwer all thoſe holy ends of
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:103318:44"/>your Confirmation, and becauſe this leads you into Religion, the firſt Act whereof is Prayer. Seeing Prayer is the firſt Act of Religion, that your beginning may not be an Error, and ſeeing it is an immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Addreſs to God, that it may be with all the Caution and Reverence of Approach, I would direct you here, and I now propoſe the uſe of Three Prayers to you, which have a particular Reſpect to your own Condition, and may be added one of them ſtill to your other Prayers, at your three daily Times of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Thankſgiving for Great Birth, and a great ſhare of Earthly Goods.</head>
               <p>O Merciful Father, and the God of all the Families of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> thou didſt make me to hope when I was yet upon the Breaſts, I was caſt upon thee from my Birth, and
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:103318:44"/>from my firſt Hours thou waſt my God. Thy Bleſſings in that my Birth were ſome of them common to me with others, and I praiſe thee for them; But ſome thou gaveſt me, O my gracious God, more pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar to my ſelf, and for theſe too I praiſe thee. For my noble Birth, and for all the following Advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of it, thoſe of Fortune, and thoſe of Education, for all I praiſe thee, and make me to praiſe thee in all thoſe Advantages, by directing and improving them all to thy Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and not admiring my own therein. Thou haſt called me to Glory and Virtue, and to no Virtue more than to Humility: May I be humble always before thee, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways conſider, that all Fleſh is Graſs, and all the Goodlineſs thereof is as the Flower of the Field, the Graſs withereth the Flower fadeth, and the Faſhion of this World, as Gaudy and Beautiful as it is, paſſeth away. So, when I thus conſider, and when
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:103318:45"/>I am thus humble, may I have a Name better than that of Sons and Daughters, an everlaſting Name which ſhall not be put out, that in Heaven it ſelf, through him who had his Birth from thee, and was thy firſt-born Son, through Chriſt my Saviour. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for a lively Senſe of Religion, and a ſincere Love thereof.</head>
               <p>LET thy Tabernacles be amiable to me, O Lord of Hoſts, let my Soul long, and even faint for the Courts of the Lord, and my Heart and my Fleſh rejoyce in God. Make my Soul to thirſt for God, for the living God; when ſhall I come and appear before God? Make thou the Mighty to give unto the Lord, to give unto the Lord Glory and Strength, to give unto the Lord the Glory due unto his Name, to Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:103318:45"/>the Lord in the Beauty of Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. As the Heart panteth after the Water-brooks, ſo let my Soul pant after thee, O God. Whom have I in Heaven but thee, and is there any thing upon Earth that I deſire in compariſon of thee? O let thy Deſire be alſo to the Work of thine own Hands, to Crown me with Mercy and loving Kindneſs, in this, and in another Life; through Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for other Graces and Virtues, and Religious Accompliſhments.</head>
               <p>I Acknowledge, O Lord, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very good Gift, and every per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Gift is from above; and ſeeing thou art ſo ready to give it, I rejoyce that it is from thee; and becauſe it is all from above, I therefore here below lift up mine Eyes unto the Hills, from whence cometh my Help. Bleſs me with all thoſe Virtues,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:103318:46"/>which are ſuitable to my Sex, and and my Condition, and my Age, and which are to make my Paſſage through this World eaſie, and that into another ſafe. With the many Goods of this World, by thy Grace give me a wiſe Contempt of it, and the loweſt Opinion of all Earthly Things, as thou haſt given me by thy Bounty, a very high Portion of them: Grant me Prudence, and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, and Succeſs in all my Actions concerning them, and yet Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Patience hereafter in all the Evils which thou may'ſt deſign for my Tryal, and which may diſturb my Enjoyment. Give me Vigour of Underſtanding, and all the goodly Endowments of it, inſtruct and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove my Soul in a daily Increaſe of all uſeful Knowledge: Enlighten it with the Knowledge of thy ſelf, the Father of Lights, and the only true God, the Knowledge of whom is eternal Liſe; that I may thus go from Strength to Strength, till I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:103318:46"/>before the God of Gods <hi>Zion,</hi> and then appear in the Glory and the Purity of Souls which follow the Lamb whitherſoever he goeth, and are the firſt Fruits to God, and to the Lamb, and are without ſpot before the Throne of God: O grant me a place before thy Throne, for the ſake of him thy Lamb, and my Redeemer Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let your Life be divided, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious part of Life, betwixt Prayer and Practice, and let no Variety di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert you more than the daily Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns of Duty in paſſing from the one to the other: Neither is to exclude, but each is ſtill to bring in the other; becauſe by Prayer you gain a Power for holy Actions, and that Power is executed by Practice, and any ſuch Power is like a Law, without Execution very Fruitleſs. A Virtuous Woman, with the Addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Greatneſs, is a publick Good, and her Influence is boundleſs, and
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:103318:47"/>ſo as to make Virtue a publick and common Good in the beſt Senſe, by making others like her ſelf: In your being one of the Virtuous Number, how much Honour ſhall you add to your Honourable Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? How much Happineſs to that other Family, into which hereafter Marriage ſhall Tranſplant you? To both Families, and to your ſelf a greater Happineſs I cannot wiſh, than the Enlargment of thoſe Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues which ſhine forth already, nor to my ſelf a nobler Satisfaction, than that Succeſs of all this my Advice, which is not doubted by him who gives it. How great a Bleſſing is ſuch a Woman I ſpoke of? <hi>Her Price is far above Rubies,</hi> above thoſe ſhe is adorned with. How great Things are ſaid of her by a mighty King, and a Wiſe one, by <hi>Lemuel,</hi> who could not chooſe but be a skilful Judge of Virtue, when he had ſo much Experience in Vice; as skilful a Judge in the Perfections of the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:103318:47"/>Sex, as when two contended for the Child, he ſhewed himſelf in the Rights thereof. That Deſcription, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1. is a part of the Prophecy his Mother taught him, <hi>verſ.</hi> 1. whoſe particular Converſation with her own Sex, muſt needs make her learned in the Accompliſhments of it? The Woman there deſcribed is a Perſon of Honour and Wealth, and ſo great enough to have her Picture drawn by a King, and the Colours to be given him by the Mother of a King: <hi>Honour her Cloathing firſt, and then Silk and Purple, her Covering of Tapeſtry, and all her Houſhold Cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Scarlet, her works praiſe her in the Gates, and her Husband is known in the Gates,</hi> (a Place of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Authority, and Greatneſs) <hi>when he ſitteth among the Elders</hi> (or Governours) <hi>of the Land,</hi> 22, 23.31, 25. Nor is her Greatneſs made therefore doubtful, becauſe her In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry ſo active in all Kinds of Work is a part of her Character and her <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:103318:48"/>for the greateſt Perſons of that Age choſe the ſame Induſtry for their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe. That when <hi>many Daughters have done Virtuouſly,</hi> you may, if not <hi>excel them all,</hi> as <hi>Verſe</hi> 29, yet imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the Virtues they excel in; your Practice is to be a Copy from that charming Picture in one part more than all, and that one Work in which her Hands were exerciſed I would recommend to you more than all the reſt, in which ſhe uſed them, <hi>ſhe ſtretcheth forth her Hand to the Poor, yea, ſhe reacheth forth her Hands to the Needy,</hi> v. 20.</p>
               <p>And here I would make it one part of my Counſels, that amongſt other Books of Scripture, you would read not only the laſt Chapter of this Book, but would begin at the firſt, and ſo go on and read all the Book, which has not only, as other Proverbs, ſhortneſs and Wit in the Language, but great Wiſdom, and profound Thought in the Senſe, and ſuch as would direct the ſeveral Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:103318:48"/>of your Life in the uſe. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it was Written by a King, who as ſuch, had greater Advantage from the high Throne he ſat on to view all Affairs, and to adviſe upon them, yet was it not Written to Kings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, but to all their Subjects, and to all Mankind. When there has been ſo much Care and Expence to teach you every thing of common Behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, you ſhould much more learn thoſe higher Arts of prudent Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, and thoſe which will give you true Accompliſhment, will make you agreeable, not only to others, in your outward Deportment, but to your ſelf, in your inward ſatisfaction. As you ſhould obſerve a regular Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod in all things you are to do, ſo ſhould you at all times have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be done. A Thought it is moſt worthy of a great Perſon to think her ſelf made for Action, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe as Happineſs, the higheſt State to which Mankind can be advanced, is in Action, ſo Greatneſs is more in
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:103318:49"/>Action then in Condition: The latter kind of Greatneſs does follow the other, and is only an unfiniſh'd Piece without it. When I ſpeak of Action, I intend not your being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways exerciſed in things high and ſerious, but only your being always in ſome Exerciſe, and ſo when the thing it ſelf may not be of ſuch a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Importance, yet it may have this Praiſe at leaſt, that it is very In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent: Then your being employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed therein will preſerve you alſo In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, and if ſometimes little good be done to others, or your ſelf, yet your doing great Evil may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented. I intend not any ſort of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe which ſhould have Toyl to Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy or Mind, but only that which ſhould be advantageous to both without oppreſſing either. Amongſt the many ſorts of Exerciſe, Reading deſerves a place, indeed it ſhould have the chief, becauſe you will then do right to the principal part, to your Underſtanding, in
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:103318:49"/>improving that which I know is ſo capable of Improvement; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe your Reading will furniſh you with ſo many uſeful Notions to make you happy in your Life, Wiſe in your Deportment, and both Wiſe and Happy in Religion. Some good Thought of the Book will have a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Printing within your Mind: Be your Reading never ſo unconcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and eaſie, it will be ſure to leave ſome Impreſſion, as often our Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, be it never ſo nimble and light, will yet leave a Mark behind it. And thus like her whom our Prince of Poets deſcribes (and as he ſeems ſo be in love with her Perfections, ſo every one would be with his Deſcription of them) you will have</p>
               <q>
                  <l>In your Mind the wiſeſt Books,</l>
                  <l>As in your Face the faireſt looks.</l>
               </q>
               <p>A modern Writer, in his Remarks up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a neighbouring Nation, obſerves the Conduct of its great Ladies to be ſuch, that he never heard of any one there who had been accuſed of Vice;
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:103318:50"/>he ſuppoſes this ſteady Virtue to have no other Cauſe, than that they are always buſie, and ſo they are not at leiſure for Thinking, and leſs for do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Ill, and then too they give no oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to others to think Ill, not of them. A Nobleman of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and lately a Miniſter of State, adviſed his Daughter to Read, or to hear Reading two or three Hours e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Day: And ſurely, if he always gave as good Advice to his Prince, for the Management of Publick Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, as here he did to his Daughter, for the Advancement of her Virtue, and private Wiſdom, he was one of the beſt Stateſmen in the World. I have ſeen a Collection of Prayers, and Spiritual Rules, Written by a very great Perſon of your Sex, and of our Nation, when very young, from the Books ſhe Read, not only to make the Writing an Exerciſe, and Action of the better ſort, but that ſhe might fix what ſhe Read with the greater Force upon her
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:103318:50"/>Mind, and that the beſt part of what ſhe had found in other Books, ſhe might always find again in her own, it might be always ready for her View, and for her Uſe. And here I cannot chooſe but wiſh that the young Nobility of the other Sex would make Reading much more their Practice; they would find it very uſeful to them, and themſelves more uſeful to their Country. At the ſame time I beg leave to offer an humble Propoſal, and well deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Requeſt to their Parents, that they would make the Education of their Sons one great part of their Care, and their Improvement in Learning one great part of their Education. I know the Failure in the preſent Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of Education, I have often de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared againſt it, and often bewail it. Never did any Nation underſtand Greatneſs more than the <hi>Romans,</hi> and in that Glorious Age when <hi>Rome</hi> had the largeſt ſhare of it, her Emperors and Noblemen eſteemed themſelves
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:103318:51"/>greater as they were more learned. They never thought there was any Attainder in Knowledg, nor did that, which was to exalt their Soul, debaſe their Blood. So high was their Ambition to excel in Letters as well as in War and Policy, that one of their Emperors reſented his Boldneſs as a Crime of High trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, who pretended to a more refi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Skill in one ſort of Learning, which was the darling Inclination the Miſtreſs of his Prince, and in which he would not admit a Rival as well as not a Partner in his Empire. It has been often ſaid, that thoſe of our Sex have no Advantage above the other, in reſpect of Learning, but what Education gives them: I hope they will not in flaming Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaiſance renounce one advantage that of Learning, by denying them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves another, this of Education, nor think it a mark of good Breeding to neglect a chief part thereof. Let there be no occaſion for the other Sex to upbraid our own, none for
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:103318:51"/>ours to be conquered by them as much in underſtanding as in Love: And at the Weapon which we have called our own, that of Knowledg. If we are conquered, let us like van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſht Forces rally again, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trieve our Honour, as Armies have ſometime done, when the Women have met them in their Flight, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braiding and inſulting over them more than their Enemies, and yet at the ſame time leſs angry with them, for not acting like Men; then with themſelves for not being ſo.</p>
               <p>Let the doing good to others, and in them to your ſelf as to the welfare of your Soul be the chief end of your Life, as you will find it one of the chief Delights thereof. In every Action conſider how far in the courſe thereof you may do good to others, and be ſure to follow it on that ſide of it, in which it leads you to the doing good, and as more is to be done, ſo much more purſue it. Every one is Born for the doing
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:103318:52"/>this, much more thoſe of ſuch a Birth as yours: They are born and placed on higher ground above others, that they may have a free and boundleſs proſpect of the wants of others, and that all the kind effects may in a gentle ſtream flow down to thoſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath them, as the Springs firſt riſe in the higheſt places to refreſh the Country all around, and the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Vallies are enriched by what flows down from the Hills above them. The Great and the Noble are not more diſtinguiſhed from the common Orders of Mankind by their Condition, then by this privilege of it, the imparting all the generous advantages to others, and as their condition is better than that of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſo they are to make the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of others too better than they found it. They are diſtinguiſh'd by the greatneſs of their Fortune, as they are able, &amp; by the greatneſs of their Mind, as they are ready for all uſeful Offices. They are like the Stars which have
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:103318:52"/>their lofty and glittering place in the World, not to be admired by the other lowly Creatures, not to dazle all things under them with their brighter Glory, but to guide and cheriſh them with their Light and Influence. The eſteem which they receive from Men, they are to give to God, they are to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> convey it farther ſtill, and carry it up to Him who is indeed the Fountain of Honour, <hi>who is higher than the higheſt,</hi> to Him whoſe Stewards they are as well in the Honour they receive as in the Riches they poſſeſs. When the late Earl of <hi>Rocheſter</hi> began to have very ſolemn apprehenſions of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther State, and very zealous thoughts of a Soul and of Spiritual things in this, when with all the flaming Piety of a Saint, and all the careful Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of a Father he began to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned for himſelf, and for thoſe next to himſelf, his Children, he wiſht that his Son might <hi>become an honest and religious Man, and ſo what he
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:103318:53"/>never could be otherwiſe, a Bleſſing and Support to his Family, that he might never be a wit, that is, one of thoſe wretched Creatures, who value themſelves upon their deſpiſing God and Religion, his Being and his Providence:</hi> This Nobleman complained, <hi>that his Children were brought into a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious world,</hi> and declared, <hi>that no Fortunes or Honours were equal to their poſſeſſing the Love and Favour of God.</hi> If there could be need to urge your willing Vertue with new Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, I ſhould tell you that you may think your ſelf ſtill more enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to adorn your Birth, and each prerogative of it with good Actions, to enlarge your Intereſt, which is ſo great already, in the World by doing them, becauſe your Sex has no other way to raiſe its Intereſt, no other paſſage to Eſteem and Power: Our Sex has many advantageous ways, as many as there are inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous Profeſſions, yours does ſeem to be ſo much deſigned for Vertue,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:103318:53"/>that it almoſt ſeems to be your Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and you to have no other, that you might be at free leiſure for it, and be devoted to it. There ſhould be the ſame ſtandard of Nobility in the thoughts of thoſe who have it, which there was in China for many hundred years, where as the Emperour himſelf (who was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Son of Heaven) was very learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and good, ſo the Nobility of thoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him and deriving from him was not from Birth, but from a likeneſs to him in great advancements of Knowledge and Vertue. It is a Notion which often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns upon me, that when I look round the World, amongſt the many enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining Objects I meet with there I find none that comes near my eye with ſo much delight as a Perſon very Great and very Good. Vertue and Beauty are often ſaid to make a Maſterpiece in the mixture: But Vertue and Greatneſs, when joyned together, make up ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing yet more perfect; Vertue, when placed ſo high, is not only ſeen better, it is ſeen more Glorious. We now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, with too much evidence, Chriſtian Piety in a great Decay, which yet, while it is ſo great in ſome, is lamented by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; If Religion muſt not live, there
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:103318:54"/>are Surviving Friends to attend the Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, and to bewail the Death: But then how importunate are to be their Prayers, how Serious are to be their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, that Chriſtian Religion now in its lower ſtate of decay and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may have at leaſt one advantage, which it had not in its firſt ſate of purity and perfection, that <hi>many Mighty and many Noble may be called,</hi> and they not onely for their own ſake, but for the ſake of others, that by the prevailing force of their Example and their Power many others may be called as well as they.</p>
               <p>There is an argument for Religion not onely from your Quality, but from your Sex. The Religious engagements are ſo much ſtronger upon your Sex, becauſe that tenderneſs of mind, which is ſo na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural to it, is no leſs natural to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Spirit of Devotion, and to the general Spirit of Chriſt's Religion, and becauſe while Men are engaged in the buſineſs and noiſe of the World, and many in the moſt noiſie part thereof, in War, you may enjoy a devout reſt at home, your Cloſet knows nothing of tumult, there at leaſt is peace and leiſure. All who have a paſſion for Piety have at the ſame time another, they are concerned
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:103318:54"/>with zeal that it may flouriſh in your Sex, and ſo may ſpread it ſelf and flouriſh in the World, that the famous Saying upon Truth may have its accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in Piety, and this, <hi>when appearing in a Form ſo beautiful, may ſtrike the eyes and charm the affections of all who behold it.</hi> Chriſtian Religion, in the firſt Ages of it, did ſomtimes ow the multiplying of its Numbers to the Zeal of your Sex: And ſo may ſtill the Holineſs ſo much deſigned and promoted by that Religion have a Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious enlargement from it. Not onely <hi>the Believing Wife then did ſanctify the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believing Husband,</hi> but the Pious Woman now may ſanctify the leſs pious Man, and her Example not only reproach him for not being good, but invite him to the being ſo hereafter. St. <hi>Hierom</hi> declared that the propagation of Vertue as much as that of the World it ſelf was due to your Sex, and therefore, when diſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with the general corruption of Mankind he fled into retirements from them, and inſtead of an abode with them choſe to dwell with the Wild beaſts of the Deſert, he ſtill continued a Religious correſpondence with many of your Sex. The reformation of that World, which now ſo fiercely we complain of, may be
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:103318:55"/>expected now from ſuch as thoſe whom St. <hi>Hierom</hi> then converſed with, and by a ſoft conveyance of all things pious from their hands: According to the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of the Chineſe Philoſopher the World conſiſts of Kingdoms, and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms conſiſt of Families; And each Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily is more in the continual view of its Governeſs, and more to be faſhioned by her. Not only the Philoſopher of China but the other of <hi>Greece,</hi> he who gave Laws to the World in Learning, as his Scholar did in War, had the ſame wiſe Notion, that the good management of Kingdoms is to follow this of Families. Indeed the influence of the Mother is great upon the Mind, as her ſhare is great in the bodily Conſtitution, of the Children; and then in this ſence too, <hi>If the Root be holy, ſo may be the Branches.</hi> Eſpecially thoſe, in the Family, of her own Sex, who are ſo much more within her view and her management, and whom her experience, in reſpect of her own Education, and then her particular knowledge of all things peculiar to her Sex do give her a more natural capacity to manage with the beſt ſucceſs. The ſaying of a Biſhop to a Courtier was no leſs ſuitable, in its Wiſdom, to his Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:103318:55"/>from whom it came, then uſeful, in its influence, to him it was directed to, <hi>When you chuſe a Wife, make your ſtrict enquiries into the qualifications, not of the Father, but of the Mother, and then you have found thoſe of the Daughter at the ſame time and in one diſcovery.</hi> And therefore, as it was the ambition of a Jewiſh Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, to be a Mother, ſo it ſhould be that of a Chriſtian, to be a good one.</p>
               <p>Amongſt the ſeveral things I have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to your practice, Faſting I have not named, much leſs preſcribed, becauſe if that can be uſeful in any part of your Age, ſome may think it not to be ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary in this part thereof. But ſurely there will be a time, when Faſting will be very uſeful, for the withdrawing our ſelves from the World, and fuell from the fire, that meat from our deſires, which does often nouriſh them more than us, as it often feeds an ulcer more than a ſounder part. Faſting will be uſeful for the making Spiritual Objects familiar to us, and for a particular enquiry into our Spiritual ſtate like that into our weekly expences, for the remembrance and the repentance of our ſins, and the appointing all the methods of ſuitable Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion againſt them, for the conſidering
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:103318:56"/>not only our Sins, in order to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking them, but our Graces too, in order to the continuance and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of them. When a great Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier was to retire from the World, who had ſeldom retired from his Enemy, he declared it to be very needful, <hi>that there ſhould be ſome ſpace between the affairs of life and the day of death:</hi> Indeed there ſhould be ſome between Life and Life, there ſhould be a Truce with the World, in order to a Peace with God, there ſhould be a Time of Reſpite, not only for the ſenſe of Taſting, but for thoſe of ſeeing and hearing, and all the Senſes; ſo we may ſeem to dye, though not dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, yet one Day at leaſt in the Week, and to better Purpoſes than <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth, we may thus act Death it ſelf, the chief Parts whereof are the Silence of the Condition, and want of Senſe. And ſo Retirement is, like Death, a ſilent and quiet State, and a remove from ſenſible Things, and it has ſomething too of the Happineſs which follows Death, in the Religious Enjoyments of it.</p>
               <p>A Method it were of great Advantage to the making you that which you ſo much deſire to be, and which all others nope to ſee you, a finiſht Work of Prudence &amp; Virtue, if you would chuſe one eminent
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:103318:56"/>for both, known to be ſo by all who know her, one of the like Quality and Condition with your ſelf, whom you may obſerve, and imitate in both. You may place her Actions before you in the faireſt Light, make her a daily Example to you in her Behaviour, that you may afterwards riſe to be an Example in yours to others. Indeed the Learned <hi>Heathen</hi> has taught us another uſe of ſuch a Method, not only to place the Actions in our ſight, that we may imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the Good, but the Perſon too in our Preſence, that we may avoid all Evil, be overaw'd againſt it, in a very innocent Magick, to carry always the Excellent Perſon with us, to ſuppoſe him ſtanding before us, where-ever we are, and reading mora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>l Lectures to us. For the latter uſe of this Method you have leſs occaſion; for the being Overawed by an imagined Preſence againſt all Evil, becauſe this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways is at ſo great a diſtance from you, and very much out of ſight: Your Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence is ſuch, and your Converſation ſo well choſen, that you almoſt ſee as little Evil in others, as others can ſee in you; there is a continual Preſence within your Self, to Overaw, and to Controle, that of pious Thoughts, and a far greater
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:103318:57"/>than what the <hi>Heathen</hi> did propoſe, there is that of God. However your Innocence is ſo great, yet ſhould you be always on your Guard, to defend and preſerve it, as the greateſt City deſerves and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires ſo much more Art and Care to keep and defend it: no Innocence is too great to be Aſſaulted, and, without a pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Care, to be conquered. Not only <hi>Lot</hi>'s Wiſe is to be remember'd, but <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi>'s too, the firſt that ever was; and were your Innocence as perfect, as in all my Raptures of Wiſhing, I could deſire, yet would it not be more perfect than Hers, and that, we know, was no more above a Conqueſt than above a Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation. I have all the vigorous Hope, (and ſurely my Hope will not deceive me here) that the early Appearance of your Underſtanding, which others ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire, and which you are happy in, will give you very much a Capacity of one kind, that of doing good, and will place you in a Condition, not ſo much of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting any greater Sin, as of avoiding it.</p>
               <p>You are now Madam, a Flower of the Faireſt Kind, in all the blooming Graces, and lively Perfections of a beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Appearance. I would take ſome Care, and I would deſire ſome from
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:103318:57"/>your ſelf, that there may be one part of you, which may not be too much like a Flower, and which may not wither. As I would exhort you to the ſecuring one part, which may not be frail, and which ſhould make the reſt of you laſting to your great Advantage, ſo I would Exhort you to nothing more, than to remember that all things upon Earth beſides are not laſting, are very frail: However you can make ſomething not to be ſo, which has a Relation to your ſelf, yet you can never make earthly Things otherwiſe by all your Art: They will not ceaſe to be ſuch, though you never ceaſe to deſire them, and to love them, they will only Infect you with their own Weakneſs, and you will be ſo much more frail your ſelf, as you more deſire them, and love them more, nor will their juſt Value be raiſed by your raiſing your Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections towards them. Seeing the Things of the World are ſuch, you may begin to argue what little Reaſon there will be to have a value for your ſelf upon things which have very little in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and then what they have not, they cannot give. So you will be moved to the not deſiring a greater ſhare in this World than you have, when, if you had
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:103318:58"/>a greater, you would only have a more bulky heap of Frailty, which ſurely is not a thing deſirable. As you will not covet more than you poſſeſs, ſo you will neither eſteem your ſelf, upon that which you enjoy, more than you ought, nor will you eſteem it more than it deſerves: And then the eager Paſſion we commonly have for things, when they are going from us, will have no place in your Mind, when you looſe them, you will not look upon things with a fond admiring Eye, which you cannot ſo much as look on long, but the fleeting Goods will ſoon be out of ſight, and out of reach. You will pay no high regard to theſe Enjoyments, which are every hour paſſing from you, and which, as ſoon as they are gone, you will ſee, could not claim any ſuch regard, when to you nothing of them ſhall remain, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but an empty waſt, and the wild and melancholy Proſpect of it. You were not more charmed with their Face, when they were coming towards you, than you ſhall be frighted with their back parts, ſo Deformed and Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous, when they are gone away beyond you. Your Diſdain will be a generous Revenge to their Inconſtancy; they fly
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:103318:58"/>from you, and at the ſame time you no leſs fly from them; you are forſaken by them, and they abhorred by you. This true Judgment of the World will make you a true Friend to, and judge of your ſelf, the Knowledge of its unſteady Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture will give you a very ſteady Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Religion, and an hearty Senſe thereof: When the Uncertainty of the World has made an Impreſſion upon your Mind, a Zeal for Religion will make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, the Contempt of that will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance the Eſteem for this, when that falls ſo much lower, this will riſe ſo much higher in your Soul, by a difference of Motion, as the things are different. It may ſeem very ſtrange, that my plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſhould be ſo importunate for your Contempt of the World, when you have ſo large an Intereſt therein; as the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice would ſeem abſurd, and very diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to him who has the largeſt ſtake in the Game, to play all the time with little Care. But if you ſhould think my Pleading to be leſs ſuitable, yet it is on your ſide, and then I cannot think any thing abſurd or unſeaſonable, which favours and promotes your Well being. This my Propoſal can never be ſo unſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, as it will be neceſſary; becauſe
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:103318:59"/>if earthly Things be treated by you with Fondneſs and Careſſes, you will ſcarce be happy in having more than others, you may be most unhappy in looſing more; as Bodies of greater Bulk are more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to Wounds, and the Wounds are more Inflamed, and Fatal. The Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſing a wealthy Share in the World does not make the deſpiſing of that leſs needful, but rather is a new Engagement to it; becauſe otherwiſe you only have ſo much more to hurt you. There cannot be a right Uſe of the World, unleſs there be a mean Opinion of it; if there be not a right uſe, if you abuſe it, that will be ſure to abuſe you too in a juſt Revenge, and will do you Miſchief. So well does one of your Sex declare in thoſe her Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Writings, which have ſo large a ſhare in the two great Accompliſhments, (Piety and Wit) where no ſhare can be too large, and ſhe Summons the whole World to hear the mighty Thing which ſhe declares, when thus ſhe Writes in Defiance to earthly Things, and for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction to Mankind, who are not very apt to bid Defiance to them.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>My Muſe pronounce aloud, there's nothing good,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nothing the World can ſhew,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nothing it can beſtew.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:103318:59"/>
               <p>Your having the meaneſt Thoughts of the World is my laſt Advice, (however when I have ſo great an Opinion of this Advice, it might alſo have been my firſt) that, like other laſt words, it may be more Imprinted upon your Memory, may go farther into your Judgment, and pierce deeper into your Affections; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this will Crown and Finiſh, and give a lively Influence to all my other Counſel, without this it cannot be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, or cannot be effectual. You will not then ſo remember your worldly Advantages, as to forget your ſelf, or rather to remember and think of your ſelf too much; but the good-natured Saying will have its force upon you, <hi>Ecclus</hi> 3.18. <hi>The greater thou art, the mote humble thy ſelf, and thou ſhalt find favour before the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If any part of my Advice ſeem leſs ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, be pleaſed to chuſe and begin with that which ſeems very eaſie, and that will carry you by gentle Steps to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; upon the practice of the eaſier part, the other will not ſeem any longer difficult: As ſometimes by a ſcarce ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible riſing we go up to the top of the Hill, and without great Toyl, only by going on, we reach it, when it appears
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:103318:60"/>at a diſtance very high, and the Aſcent very troubleſome. You are ready, I know, to meet Religion, in every way in which it is coming towards you, and you give it all the joyful Embraces at the Meeting, and you are ready to take all Good Advice, at the ſame time you ſo little want it, and are fit to give it. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing which wears the Badg, or comes in the Name of Religion has more than <hi>a Cup of cold Water,</hi> ſomething warm and vigorous, and hearty from you, and ſurely you <hi>ſhall not looſe your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</hi> To Propoſals of Religion you always give an eaſie and liberal Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment, and you are not therefore to be oppreſt, as Perſons eaſie in Acceſs, and bountiful in Entertainment, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times are by troubleſome and impoſing Gueſts. My Inſtructions ſhould be uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, but not ſevere; like a well modell'd Poem, they ſhould have Profit, and Pleaſure too, they ſhould be Healthful, as Exerciſe and good Diet, not unplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant as Phyſick, eſpecially where little of Diſeaſe is to be removed, and a ſofter Method will prevent: When the Mind is of ſo untainted a Conſtitution, the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian may be as much a Courtier as he pleaſes, there can only be need of ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:103318:60"/>to prevent, and not to Cure. If any part of my Counſels ſeem leſs ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to your preſent Age, that has a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign beyond it, to become a ſtanding Rule for all your Life; and why ſhould not good things, as well as ſome ill things, and Poiſons have a laſting force, and work at the diſtance of many Years? I would thus lay up for you a Treaſure of Inſtructions, which may hereafter <hi>make you Rich in good Works,</hi> and I would in this Senſe <hi>lay up for you a good Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt the time to come,</hi> a Foundation as ſtrong as good, that you may <hi>be built up in your moſt holy Faith,</hi> and may never be liable to any Fall or Ruine. My Deſigns cannot be narrow and ſhort, when your Welfare is in view, and in purſuit; and how charming is the Thought of my having done any thing to advance it in every part of your Life! So you may be that to me, which an old Chriſtian Writer calls a Prince of his Time in an Epiſtle to him, <hi>The glorious Ornament of all my Labours,</hi> if I may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to Labours, and may deſerve ſuch an Ornament. A Secretary to four Popes Writ a Book of Advice upon Studies and Learning, Dedicated it to an Illuſtrious Lady, and he intended it for her Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:103318:61"/>A Grammar was Written for the Uſe of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> when very young, and Preſented to her Mother, <hi>Catherine</hi> Queen of <hi>England:</hi> I profeſs not here to ſend you Learned, but Religious Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and not to teach you Words, but Things, the beſt, and the greateſt Things, and no other Language but of <hi>the better Country, that is, the Heavenly.</hi> I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent only ſuch Inſtructions, as upon the Command of King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt, Dr. <hi>Williams,</hi> (afterwards Biſhop, and Lord Keeper) writ for the uſe of the Lady <hi>Catherine Manners,</hi> Daughter to the then Earl of <hi>Rutland,</hi> and Married to the then Marqueſs of <hi>Buckingham.</hi> When the Author ſent thoſe Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the Marqueſs, he declared thus in his Letter which attended them; <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is moſt neceſſary for the obtaining, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples for the Augmenting, Reſolution for Vie defending a true Faith and Profeſſion.</hi> The young Marchioneſs was then not only to be Inſtructed in the Doctrin of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> but to be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted from another, of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That every thing now propoſed, may ſo much more prevail for your ſake, and
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:103318:61"/>for mine, be pleaſed to Pray in that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing Language of the Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lord of all Power and Might, who art the Author, and Giver of all good Things, graft in my Heart the Love of thy Name, encreaſe in me true Religion, Nouriſh me with all Goodneſs, and of thy great Mercy keep me in the ſame, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> Amen.</p>
               <p>And now, <hi>whatſoever things are pure, whatſoever things are lovely, whatſoever things are of good report; if there be any Virtue, if there be any Praiſe, think on theſe things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>May you obſerve all theſe Rules, and whatſoever Rules may be added to theſe, that you may have an Addition too of Bleſſings, and a far more exceeding Weight of Glory, a Weight which ſhall not be Uneaſie, or Oppreſs; but the heavier it is, ſhall be ſtill more eaſie. May the holy Practice, you began ſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry early, end very late, may it never end; but O let it be continued in the Heavenly, in the endleſs State, not only continued, but <hi>as high as the Heaven is, in compariſon of the Earth,</hi> ſo much more heighten'd too. May you always be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:103318:62"/>with a Deſire, a ſteady and refined Deſire of Heaven, as a Place not only of everlaſting and unchangable Happineſs, but alſo of everlaſting and unchangable Holineſs. May you be happy now in a Religious Practice, and happy hereafter in the Reward thereof. In the mean time the view of both, of your Practice and your Reward, makes another happy, the unworthy Writer, and</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Madam, Your Lady ſhips moſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nworthy And moſt humble Servant.</hi> J. P.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer before the receiving of the Sacrament, with regard to its being Commanded by God, and deſired by us.</head>
               <p>O Moſt gracious God, the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and in him the Father of Mercies too, and the God of all Comfort, let thy Mercies, and thy Comfort, I moſt
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:103318:62"/>humbly, I moſt earneſtly beſeech thee, be always preſent to me, and particularly at this time, and at ſuch times as this. Thou haſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed a Sacrament for the Health and the Strength of my Soul; O make me to rejoyce in that Appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment now, as I am to live, by the right uſe of it, hereafter. Thou haſt given me a Command, O my God, to receive it, and thou haſt given me the priviledge of receiving it: O let this Command at leaſt be performed by me, that the Breaches of all thy o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Commands may be forgiven to me. O let not this Priviledge be deſpiſed, that all the other Priviled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and Benefits may not be forfeited. Thy dying Son has ſpoken to me, and in Words which were almoſt Written in his Blood, and which I ſhould be ready to Seal with mine; <hi>do this in remembrance of me.</hi> When he bids me, and when thou repeateſt what he ſaid, with new Engagements, ſhall not I <hi>do this,</hi> and every thing? Can I
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:103318:63"/>chuſe but do it, when it is to be done in remembrance of him, the Thought of whom is to be moſt pleaſing to me, his Name is as Ointment pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red forth, his Mouth is moſt ſweet, and he altogether lovely? Can any thing be needful to make me remember him? Can any thing be able to make me forget him, till I can forget my ſelf? It yet there be no neceſſity for any thing to preſerve the Memory of him, there is one for the performing what thou Commandeſt. If nothing can make me forget thy Love, and the Son of thy Love, yet I am to ſhew that I do not forget him, in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring his Precept. From thy Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs I have received a Command, and now from thy Grace a Deſire for the obſerving of it. O grant me all the Meaſures, the overflowing Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of thy Grace for the Executing thy Command, and my Deſire, and thy Grace, (as much need as I have thereof, will be ſufficient for me, I can do all things through Chriſt who
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:103318:63"/>ſtrengthens me. Lord, I deſire, help thou my Weakneſs in deſiring, and much more in the performing. Be thou a Sun and a Shield, a Sun to Chear and Enlighten, a Shield to ſave and defend my Soul. Gird me with Strength, who have none of my own, and let thine ſo wound my Spiritual Enemies, that they may not be able to riſe, but fall under my Feet. Let there be no want of Grace from thee, and in me no want of Will: I am Feeble and Weak, but thou, O Lord, art Strong and Migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and thy ſtrength is made perfect in my Weakneſs, and will make that perfect too. As thy Mercy rejoyces againſt Judgment; ſo does thy Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er againſt Infirmity, and thy Power, the more I want of it, will rejoyce ſo much more, if my uſe of thy Gift be ſuitable to what thou haſt given: Thou giveſt to will and to do of thy good Pleaſure; for the partaking of this thy Holy, this thy bleſſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thou haſt given me to will, O
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:103318:64"/>give me to do of the good Pleaſure, which thou haſt declared for me, and declared to me in the Merits, and for the fake of thy beloved Son, and my never enough beloved Saviour Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Another Prayer before the receiving of the Sacrament, with a regard to God's Favour, and our Qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in our Approaches to the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O Thou the God of my Mercy, and the God of my Salvation, accept, I pray thee, thy moſt unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Servant in that Duty in which I ſhould appear moſt worthy, and accept my Weakeſt Service, where the beſt of my Strength ſhould be employed. O thou High and lofty One that inhabiteſt Eternity, whoſe Name is Holy, thou dwelleſt in the High and Holy Place, with him al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that is of a contrite and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Spirit, to revive the Spirit of the Humble, and to revive the Heart of the Contrite: O make
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:103318:64"/>me contrite in Heart, and humble in Spirit, that thou may'ſt dwell with me, that I may dwell with thee in thy Houſe, and at thy Table. For thy Son's ſake, for thy own ſake, for thy Mercies ſake, contend thou not for ever, and be not thou always angry, that the Spirit may not fail before thee, and the Soul which thou haſt made. Thou haſt ſeen my ways, O heal me; lead me, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore Comforts to me, and to my Mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, to all thoſe Powers within me, which mourn for my Sins againſt thee: Be thou mine everlaſting Light, and the Days of my Mourning ſhall be ended. Make me firſt to waſh my Hands in Innocency, and then admit me to compaſs thine Altar, O Lord of Hoſts, my King and my God. And how bleſſed are they who dwell in thy Houſe, they ſhall be always praiſing thee! A Day in thy Courts is better than a thouſand. I confeſs my Sins, O do thou forgive them: I grieve for my Sins, O make me to rejoyce in the Pardon of them. <hi>[Here remember as much as may be, and confeſs the particular Sins of your Life]</hi> Too long, alas, have I lived, O make me to live no longer, in a Correſpondence with them. Too long have I born the Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, and thou the Defiance, of them.
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:103318:65"/>Too long have I been at Peace with my Luſts, and then all the time not at Peace with thee, and with my ſelf: I now Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim War againſt them, do thou teach my Hands to War, and coyer my Head in the Day of Battle, give me the Shield of thy Salvation, and thy right Hand ſhall hold me up, and thy Gentleneſs ſhall make me great. Give thou to me Grace and Glory, and make me to live a Godly Life, and then no good thing ſhalt thou with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold from me now in the Sacrament, nor afterwards in any other part of Religion, or any part of my Life. Cloath my Soul with the Garments of Salvation, cover it with a Robe of Righteouſneſs, as a Bride adorns her ſelf with her Jewels. Let that Pardon, which this Sacrament is the Seal of, be extended to all my ſinful Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections in the receiving of it. The Pardon of my Sins, and the Acceptance of my ſelf, the great Benefits of thy Sacrament, and a true Frame of my Soul, that the benefits may be mine, and I may be thine for ever, vouchſafe, O God, who art rich in Mercy, to grant to me who am poor in Performance; O grant all to me in the Name, in the Righteouſneſs, in the Mediation of thy only Son, and my only Redeemer, Thy bleſſed Son, and my ever
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:103318:65"/>bleſſed Redeemer, and I ask all again in his holy Words, Our Father, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe Prayers are ſo much lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, becauſe it is ſuppoſed that good Perſons ſet a part more time for this Occaſion, and ſo they are more at leiſure for a length, and they have then a ſtronger Devotion for the bearing it; and the Retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at ſuch a Seaſon is to take off our Thoughts from the World, and to this Deſign Prayer is very uſeful, and the more we are in that Duty, the more we are out of the World; the nearer we approach to God in Prayer, the farther we are from the World in Thought.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Here follows a ſhorter Prayer to the ſame Preparatory Purpoſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O Bleſſed Jeſu, who haſt Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, who haſt Died for me, whoſe Sufferings and Death I am now to remember, make me, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy as I am, not to Eat and Drink Unworthily in this ſolemn Remembrance: That Worthineſs
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:103318:66"/>which I have not, be pleaſed to give me, O give me that which thou haſt purchaſed for me, that which I have ſo little, which thou haſt ſo much of, thou haſt enough for me, and for all Mankind beſides me; I ask it for my ſelf, and for all, now, and ever. <hi>Amen. Devout Ejaculations at the Holy Table before the receiving of the Sacrament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>THou haſt invited me, O merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Lord, to thy Table, and lo I come; Thou wilt receive whom thou haſt invited, O receive me graciouſly.</p>
               <p>Lo, I come, to do thy Will, O my God, I am contented, I delight to do it; and let thy Law be always within my Heart.</p>
               <p>In Burnt-offerings and Sacrifices for Sin thou haſt had no Pleaſure, Sacrifice and Offering thou wouldeſt not; but a Body haſt thou prepared, thy Sons Body to be Crucified; O let a Soul too be Prepared, my Soul to be Offered.</p>
               <p>O moſt Kind and Compaſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Jeſu, who didſt Exhort the
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:103318:66"/>Daughters of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> at the time of thy death not to Weep for thee, but to Weep for themſelves, and for their Children; have a favourable Regard to all my Weeping for my ſelf, and for my Sins, upon this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of thy Death.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Devout Ejaculations after the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of the Sacrament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I Have received, O my God, and I Praiſe thee, I Glorify thee, I Adore thee for the Honour of thy Command, and the Favour of thy Leave to do ſo.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt given me Bread from Heaven, Thou haſt given me Wine that maketh glad the Heart of Man, glad with a ſpiritual Joy which thus begins in this World, and is not to end in another.</p>
               <p>I did hunger and thirſt after the Righteouſneſs which is offer'd in this Sacrament, and O let me now be filled, let me now be bleſſed.</p>
               <p>Let all the ſpiritual Vertues of thy Body and Blood, O moſt holy Jeſu,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:103318:67"/>enter into my Soul, enter deep into it, may they enliven, may they no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, may they ſtrengthen it to an everlaſting Life. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>However this Diſcourſe has nothing to deſerve ſuch a Concluſion, yet I ask leave to give the ſame to my Diſcourſe, which a <hi>Jew</hi> did to his, when he had Written a Catechiſm, (by him named Good Doctrine) of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Religion, <hi>According to the Sincerity of my Purpoſe remember me, O God: The Jew</hi> ſays yet more, which I cannot pretend to ſay, with that Confidence which is more pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar to <hi>Jews</hi> in the high Thoughts of their Favour with God. <hi>I ſhall not bluſh, nor be aſhamed in this World, nor in that to come, but thou wilt give me the Portion common to thoſe by whom many have been Exhorted to Piety and Righteouſneſe; for they ſhall ſhine as Stars, ſo, ſo let it pleaſe thee.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:103318:67" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
